Dept idea what the future could look like with Yaoi
Dept idea what the future could look like with Yaoi
So she gives da ice´ elevator a nice new way or we could go out to hang out
So she gives da ice´ elevator a nice new way or we could go out to hang out
So
So
and
and
then
then
you
you
because
because
free
自由
it
it
remembrance
remembrance
between
between
ah
ah
distinguished guests
各位貴賓
Tonight's speech was supposed to be hosted by Vice President Chen Jianren
今天晚上的演講本來應該由陳建仁副院長主持
But because Vice President Chen Jianren had to go abroad for work
但因為陳建仁副院長有要工出國
so let me represent
所以由我來代理
Then the Senate of the Lee Academy was born in 1932
那麼李院參院士是1932年出生
He told me not to talk too much
他因為交代我不要講太多
so what about me
所以我呢
I didn't prepare his information first.
就事先沒有把他資料先備熟
So let me just say
所以我簡單的說一點
Well because he's very polite
那麼因為他非常客氣
Then he is the 20th academician of our academy
那麼他是本院科學主帝二十屆院士
Academician Li received his bachelor's and master's degrees from the Department of Agrochemistry, National Taiwan University
李院士在台大農化系取得學士跟碩士畢業
Then came to the United States in 1958
之後在1958年到美國
University of Elva
埃爾瓦大學
Read in 1960 to get Ph.D. in biochemistry
讀書在1960年得到生化學博士
Professor at Johns Hopkins University
時候就在約翰霍普金斯大學擔任教授
until now
一直到現在
Then his research field is mainly this
那麼他的研究領域主要是這個
In-class research
堂內研究
His research in this hall
他這個堂內研究
my limited knowledge
我有限的知識
Known is a very difficult field
所知是一個非常困難的一個領域
then he is here
那麼他在這個
A very cutting-edge foundation in the field
在這個領域從事非常尖端的基礎
scientific research
科學研究
Then the hall is one of the main components of the cell
那麼堂內是細胞的主要成分之一
To understand the function of the hall, you must first decipher the structure
要瞭解堂內的功能必須先破解去結構
Over the years, a series of internal quantifications developed by Academician Li
那麼多年來李院士發展的一系列堂內定量
qualitative analysis
跟定性分析方法
Has become a model of micro analysis in the hall
已經成為堂內微量分析的典範
Then there is a great achievement in this area
那麼在這方面有極高的成就
also won many awards
也獲得了許多獎
Then he told me not to talk about it.
那麼他交代我這一講都不要講
so i'm left
所以我就剩下來
Please refer to yourself
請各位自行參考
In fact it's not just this
事實上不只是這個
not just this there are many
不只是這個有很多
Well, what he's accomplished in this area is outstanding.
那麼他在這方面的成就非常傑出
then in education
那麼在教育
Research and other contributions are very admirable
研究等方面的貢獻都非常令人欽佩
Well of course he has an identity
那麼當然他還有個身份
He is Dean Li's brother
他是李院長的哥哥
Well, I think everyone knows this
那麼這個我想大家都知道
But what is the topic of his speech today?
可是他今天要演講的題目呢
It's beyond everyone's expectations
很出乎大家的意料之外
He's talking about the Columbian influence on Taiwanese food
他是要講哥倫部對台灣食物的影響
I saw this topic two days ago
我在兩個禮不多久以前看到這個題目
Surprised
大吃一驚
I asked Academician Li, do you really want to talk about this topic?
我問李院士你真的是要講這個題目
real
真的
so i'm very curious
所以我非常好奇
very curious
非常好奇
Because this seems to have nothing to do with the hall
因為這個跟堂內好像錯不在一起
But it seems to be wrong again
可是好像又錯了在一起
We now give warm applause to Mr. Lee Yen Choi
我們現在熱烈掌聲歡迎李延財議員
Thank you Wang Guoyuan
謝謝王國遠的
Thank you for your help
謝謝各位貿易理常幫我忙
This is also surprising
地區這也是很意外
Usually, this kind of speech is an expert's speech.
平常這種就是講言是專家講
A less specialized way of talking about specialized things
講專的事情比較不專的方法
what about me
那麼我這個呢
Is to talk about the influence of public forces Taiwanese food
是講公共部隊台灣食物的影響
then you can ask
那麼你們可以問
What qualifications do I have to say this?
我是憑什麼資格來講這個呢
i am not a historian
我並不是歷史學家
not a sociologist
也不是社會學家
not a linguist
也不是語言學家
But what?
不過呢
The Duoduo sofa we make biochemical has something to do with food
我們做生化的多多沙發跟食物是有關係的
I've also led for several years on food-related panels in the U.S.
我也带了好几年的在美国有关食物的专题讨论
then you can tell
那么你可以看得出来
Our lab also prints six or seven lessons of this cookbook
我们的实验室也印出六七本这个食谱的课
I think such words from netizens
我想网友的这样的字
Is it enough to talk about this topic?
够不够讲这个题目呢
enough enough
够够够
then it can be done
那就可以进行
then the world is so big
那么世界这么大
Well, 26 of these major crops in the world
那么其中世界上26个的这个主要作物
Eight of these are from the so-called New World
其中的8种是来自于所谓新大陆
Then these 8 are the Malin tree fan tree
那么这8个就是马林树藩树
Cornwood Tree Tomato Chili
玉米木树番茄辣椒
happening chocolate and vanilla
發生巧克力和香草
I'll talk about every
我會講到每一個
After this bug every
這個bug以後每一個
Plus a lot more
另外還加很多東西
so i now explain
那麼我現在說明
This screen we are talking about
這個我們講的這個螢幕上面
mostly in Chinese
多半都是中文
Alto Control
也有中音對照
also only in english
也有只有英文的
But English is very simple
不過英文是非常簡單
So I hope you can understand
所以希望你們能夠了解
I left English on purpose
我這是故意把英語留下來
Then in this bug
那麼這個bug裡頭
Seven of them are made in Taiwan
其中七種是在台灣做的
So start with this
那麼先從這個
Dried sweet potatoes and sweet potatoes
番薯乾薯地瓜講起
Sweet potatoes are often used in Taiwan
台灣很常常用番薯
to describe its own
來比喻它自己的東西
Then if you turn around late at night
那麼你到晚夜去翻的話
you can see a lot
就可以看到很多很多
Seven hundred are all about sweet potatoes and dried potatoes
七百個都是有關地瓜乾薯
sweet potato thing
番薯的事情
So
那麼
this is my name
這個呢 我叫
panzi food sweet potato tomato blah blah blah
番茲號 食物 番薯番茄 等等等等
This is actually not too strange
這個 其實也不是太奇怪
because you are watching
因為你在看
You also read the previous things
以前的東西 你也看
zucchini pepper a lot of stuff
胡瓜胡椒 很多胡的東西
Most of this nonsense is pointing
這個胡的東西 多半都是指著
Something from the West or the North Food
西方或者北方來的東西 食物
So what about Fanzi? This is Fanzi's.
那麼番茲呢 這個番茲的
And the food, mostly from the new road
食物呢 多半都是從新道路來的
So you just watch Fanzi
所以呢 你就看番茲
where the hell did the old one come from
舊小的到底是從哪裡來的
What about a lot of this food? Its name is
很多這個食物呢 它的名稱是
with this history
帶有這個歷史
factor there
因素在那裡
then let's talk
那麼我們就先講
Gansu liquid melon
甘肅 液瓜
What about this, of course, in Latin?
這個呢 當然有拉丁文
Don't touch it, Watatas
一不摸啊 瓦塔塔斯
five thousand years ago
五千年前
Believe in what you say
信話 信話就是說
human begins
人類開始
start planting start improving
开始种开始改良
Then theirs were planted 5,000 years ago
那么他们那个是五千年前种的东西
not what we see now
并不是现在我们看到的东西
So 5,000 years ago it was many of these farmers and so on
那么五千年前是其中很多農夫等等
Both improved very differently
都改良非常不一样
So don't think that five thousand years will be so good
所以不要以为五千年就有这么这么好的
where is the sweet potato
这个地瓜在那里
Sorry this point can only
很抱歉这个point只能
Can only be used in the middle of this
只能用在这个中间这个
Then both sides can not see
那么双边就不能看得到
But you can do this progressive movement to the left and right
不过你可以做这个进步运动到左右
then you can also see
那么你也可以看得出来
This one looks like the millennium flower, right?
这个呢很像千年花对不对
In fact, this is the subject of the same genus
其实这个是同属的主物
Then I will talk about the innermost thing later.
那么以后会讲到最内的东西之物呢
There were many, many
里头当时的很多很多
So
那么
Let me tell you, there is no need to talk about this, sweet potatoes can also be boiled, baked, and many things can be cooked
我告訴大家,這個不必講,地瓜也可以煮,可以烤,很多東西都可以做
Honey sweet potato will be discussed in more detail later
蜜番薯以後會講得比較詳細一點
One advantage is that the sweet potato experience can also be eaten
有一個好處就是地瓜經驗也可以吃的
I just ate this even if I didn’t speak Chinese
我剛才不是說中文也吃過這個
How did sweet potatoes come to Taiwan?
蜜番薯怎麼到台灣來呢?
there are many stories
這個還有很多故事
What I want to introduce to you now is the honey sweet potato cultural system
我現在要向大家介紹的就是蜜番薯文化製
This is quoted in this book
這個這本書裡頭引用起來
Spanish sailors first brought this dried potato to the Philippines
西班牙水手先把這個乾薯傳到菲律賓
Do you remember that the Philippines was controlled by Spain for a while
你記得菲律賓有一段時期是在西班牙管制
So of course the Spaniards can bring this thing to the Philippines
所以期間當然西班牙人可以把這個東西到菲律賓
The Philippines can be considered part of the country of Spain
菲律賓可以算是西班牙的國家的一部分
It is strictly prohibited to export and cannot be exported
它是嚴禁出口,不能夠出口
However, what is forbidden
不過,怎麼嚴禁的東西
Everyone knows how Yan Duoduo has a way
大家就知道,怎麼嚴多多有辦法
move out, can do that
搬出來,能做那麼出來
Not only the Chinese, other countries will be like this
不僅是中國人,其他的國家都會這樣
Hu Jianren and Chen Yi introduced China from the Philippines
胡建仁陳毅就從菲律賓引進中國
It's just a sneak attack
就是偷偷打擊了
Exactly a few years later, in 1993, Hu Jian had a violent attack
恰好幾年以後,1993年,胡建就發生了激防
Hu Jian already had a lot of aggressive defenses
胡建本來就有很多激防的
Hell is not good and the weather is not good
地域也不好,天氣也不好
So this year, Chen Yi's son
所以這一年,陳毅的兒子
The students at that time called him to grow sweet potatoes
當時的學生叫他種番薯
to improve blood volume
來改善血量的重勁
Then, there is another post, Chen Yi posted in Dong Huan
然後,另外有寄在,陳毅在冬歡寄
In 1963, he talked about the aboriginal farming in Gansu
1963年講到原住民種這個甘肅的事情
Spaniards once also came to the northern part of Taiwan
西班牙人曾經也來過台灣的北部
At that time, it may also bring Gansu
那時候也可能帶來甘肅
Then there is also evidence that redhead fish and Taitung are growing in Gansu
那麼紅頭魚、台東也有證據在種甘肅
This was discovered by the South China people
這是華南人發現的
Of course, it is very likely that it emerged from the other side.
當然非常可能是從對岸浮現出來
Well, especially if you've heard
那麼尤其大家聽說過
When Zheng Chenggong first arrived in Taiwan
鄭成功剛到台灣的時候
he wasn't prepared
他並沒有什麼準備
That is to say, he did not prepare the food for his 30,000 people
就是說沒有準備他的三萬人的這個食糧
Fortunately, Taiwan has been able to grow Gansu
不過幸虧台灣已經能夠種甘肅
According to the Spanish cultural system
據西班牙人發生文化制
They can plant Gansu for two months
他們種兩個月的甘肅就可以了
three month army
三個月的軍隊
so pretty good
所以相當好
So why are sweet potatoes sweet?
那麼番薯為什麼甜呢
Take a few people. Small sweet potatoes are sweet
拿幾個人小的番薯是甜的
Not very
不很
It is directly influenced by the fact that sweet potatoes are sweet
就是直接受番薯是甜的
why is it sweet
為什麼甜呢
Because it has a little more length
因為它的長質比較多一點
a little more than this usual sheep feather
比這個平常的羊羽多一點
But this one is only a small part
不過這個一部只是一個小部分
Then the sweet potato contains electricity to remove catabolites
那麼番薯裡頭有電除分解美
So it can decompose the electricity in the sweet potato
所以能夠把番薯裡頭的電分解
So if you are interested in making a comparison
所以你只要有興趣做個比較的話
If you bake the sweet potatoes in a resistance oven, they won't be sweet
你把番薯用電阻烤爐烤的話就不甜了
not too sweet
不太甜了
So if you are afraid of sweets, I think few people are afraid of sweets
所以你怕甜的話我想很少人怕甜
If so, you can use a resistance grill to bake it.
的話可以用電阻烤去烤
As long as you go with a normal oven
只要用平常的烤爐去的話
Just dry and crispy but very sweet
就乾酥就非常甜
feel very sweet
覺得非常的甜
There was a candied radish just now.
剛才有一個菜脯裡頭也是
put a handful of dried crisps in
一把乾酥放在
If you boil it slowly in a normal pot
在平常的鍋子裡慢慢燒的話
becomes very very sweet
就變得非常非常甜
Everyone, I think anyone who has a commemoration of his release knows this.
大家我想有出放紀念的人都曉得這一點
So what is the nutrition of sweet potato
那麼甘蔬的營養是怎麼樣
The biggest feature is that it has vitamin A very very high
最大的特徵是它有微生素A非常非常高
This is 262% of Rixu, which is three times
這是日許的262%就是三倍
just too much
就是太多了
not too much
不是太多的
very many
很多很多
This one is better than this Potato than sheep feather
這個是比這個Potato比羊羽是很好
Others of course there are many of this
其他當然有很多這個
so-called micronutrients
所謂微生營養上面
is very important one has
是非常重要的一種都有
Then if we talk about heat
那麼假如講熱量的話
Sweets and vegetables are not too high
甘蔬並不太高
Even with this daily allowance, it’s not too high
就是用這個日許的量來講是並不太高
So
那麼
What is the production volume of Fangen
凡屬的生產量是怎樣呢
if use this
假如用這個
The average beauty is the average
美人平均就是人均的凡屬
In terms of production volume
生產量來講呢
yes
是
Papua New Guinea
Papua New Guinea
is the highest
是最高
Solomon D'Or
Solomon D'Or
big bed is
大臥是
one hundred sixty seven four
一百六十七四
you can tell
你可以看得出來
No matter what you play, rodless
無論你玩的、無竿的
are higher
都比較高一點
not in
並不是在
beautiful countries
美作的各國
So it can be seen that this is already
所以可見這個已經是把
new big thing
新大的東西
Useful elsewhere
用到別的地方就非常有用
So
那麼
Of course you can also see
當然你也可以看得出來
these things are
這些東西都是
Can't grow rice
不能夠種米
A place where wheat cannot be grown
不能夠種麥的地方
So
那麼
now for this
現在來講這個
Potatoes
Potatoes
This Qinghua must be earlier
這個青華必須要早一點
Evidence from 10,000 years ago
一萬年前就有證據
People's species
人家種
Of course not a smaller one like this
當然不像這樣比較小塊的
I haven't seen it either
我也沒看過
In 10,000 years, the future is not here
一萬年就未來還沒在這裡
But according to archaeologists
不過據考古學家來說
not that big
並不是那麼大的
The Poleto Solanum Tuvarossum
這個Poleto Solanum Tuvarossum
The languages ​​spoken are very different
各種語言裏頭說話非常不一樣
Spanish speaks Pata
西班牙講Pata
It comes from this native language
這是從這個土語傳來的
another kind of speech
另外一種講話
Like this Art Appel in Dutch
就像這個荷蘭語的Art Appel
It's an earthy apple
就是土意的蘋果
Another kind of speech is Italian Russian
另外一種講話是義大利俄國的
Shoes
Tufli
This is the very expensive shiitake mushroom from France.
這個就是法國的非常名貴的那種香菇
what is shiitake
叫什麼香菇
I forgot
我忘了
but anyway
不過反正
That's it
就是這樣
This Italian uses this
這個義大利人就用這個
The Germans are changing it a bit, called Karatover
德國人就在改一點,叫做卡拉托弗
Germans also use art apple, art is to the apple
德國人也用art apple,art就是to the apple
Russia also uses this Karatover
俄國也用這個卡拉托弗
French is the same as the local Marlins, potatoes are the same as the Continental
法語當地馬林斯一樣,土豆是大陸一樣
In Ruiyu is Marlins, and Gagaimo
瑞瑜裡頭是馬林斯,另外加格伊摩
Gagimo is when they brought in
加格伊摩是他們引進來的時候
It's Gabba from Sofa, which was called Gagarda back then
是從沙發加巴,那時候叫做加格爾達
so it's called gageimo
所以它叫做加格伊摩
This Puttlang is also like the French style
這個普特特朗也是像法式一樣
It is rented by the old party, and its scope is wider
是舊方的租,而且它的範圍比較廣一點
To remember this soldier and this generation
要記住這個小兵和時代這一代年代
wars among european countries wars other than climate
歐洲各國戰爭除了氣候以外的戰爭
So get big
所以弄到大氣方
However, most of these countries can still grow wheat
不過多半這些國家裡還可以種小麥
Therefore, it is not necessary to rely entirely on this Potato for rescue.
所以不一定完全靠這個Potato來救護
So they are more manageable
所以他們都比較可以過得去
But Alan
不過愛蘭
Ailan is the most popular snack for Potato
愛蘭這個是受Potato買零食的最多
There is a good reason for this
這個是很有理由的
makes sense
很有道理的
We have been to Ireland twice
我們到去過愛蘭兩次
Then I learned a lot about the history and geography of Ailan
那麼其中學到不少愛蘭的歷史地理
The geography of Ailan is
愛蘭的地理這個是
It was hundreds of years ago
本來就是幾百年前
Ailan mainly develops here
愛蘭是主要是在這邊來發展
This area is better
這邊地域比較好一點
All kinds of things grow faster
種東西都長得快一點
but later
不過以後呢
british light loveland after
英國人清淡的愛蘭以後
take the original geography
就把原來的地理
The man who loves blue comes here
這個愛藍人來到這邊來
Here is the land is very bad
這邊就是土地是非常壞的
You can tell from this
你可以看得出來從這個
This is also the image I made last year
這是也是我去年造的像
is very convenient
就是非常方釀
many stones
石頭很多
nothing looks right
什麼東西都長得正不起
Only potatoes can
只有Potato才能
In order to grow up in this kind of place
才能在這種地方可以長得起來
so what
所以呢
Originally the basic thing of the Inca Empire was Potato
本來印加帝國的基本事物是Potato
And after it spread to Europe in 1570
然後一五七零年傳到歐洲以後呢
Ailan is the first to collect money on a large scale
愛藍首先大大規模的財納
late 16th century
16世紀末
big success
栽培大成功
Not very successful
不大成功也不行
Now they don't have anything to eat
現在他們都沒有什麼東西好吃
so what
所以呢
they succeeded
他們成功的
Able to export to European countries
能夠輸出到歐洲各國
So the personality is super positive all at once
所以人格都超正就是一下子
this
這
these decades
這幾十年來
Just from five a day
就一下子從一天五
million to eight million
百萬到八個百萬
increase very quickly
增加很快很快
The increase is fast, of course there is something wrong
增加很快當然有毛病了
so why is there a problem
那麼為什麼有毛病呢
Because other crops cannot grow
因為其他的作物不能長
only grow potatoes
只能種土豆
Then it becomes monocrop
然後就變成單作物
Single crop problems are many
單作物毛病是很多
Because disease is easy to come
因為病存害很容易來
So get this kind of here is an example
所以搞到這種這是一個例子
black spot
黑斑病
The disease of potatoes
現在土豆的病存
This disease still exists
這種病害還是有
not completely wiped out
並不是完全消滅了
But then it was the most powerful
不過那時候是最厲害
Then what
然後呢
After finding the disease
找到病存害以後
Then most of the potatoes just fell off.
那麼這個土豆就大部分就純是掉了
So make this big famine in Aran
所以弄成這個愛蘭的大饑荒
Then what
然後呢
It can be seen that this very, very powerful hope
可以看得出來這個非常非常厲害的這個希望
Therefore, the population will decrease greatly after this place exists.
所以有這個地方以後人口是大減
From this number reduced like this
從這個數字減少這麼樣
It is one of the four languages ​​of Taiwan
就是台灣的四文之一
some are immigrants
有的是移民
some are dead
有的是就是過世
So this has a great influence on Ailan
所以這個對愛蘭是很大的影響
And the result of immigration
而且移民的結果
It also means that at least two presidents of the United States are pure Irish
也是說美國的至少有兩個總統是純粹的愛蘭人
Well, Obama now also says he is one of the eight writers
那麼歐巴馬現在也說他是八文之一
Or one of the few texts is the Irishman
或者幾文之一是愛蘭人
No matter how many who is one of the few texts
不管是幾 誰是幾文之一
Anyway, this is a big problem
反正這個是很大的問題
how to solve this problem
這個問題怎麼解決呢
Later, it was more disease-resistant and disease-resistant from the United States.
後來還是從美國比較抗病抗病
Insect-resistant species reintroduction
抗蟲的種再輸
Only input can solve this problem
有輸進去才解決這個問題
It turns out that Mallinson's origin is in
原來馬林遜的原產地是在
Biru is about the middle of Bolivia
碧如跟波利維亞差不多中間的
this is very famous
這個是非常有名的
Lake Titicaca
Lake Titicaca
what about this lake
這個湖呢
So it's interesting to say
所以有趣的就是說
the people who live in this lake
它住在這個湖裡頭的人
don't live on land
並不是住在土地上面
They took this little grass that grows in the water
他們把這個水裡長出來的微草
How many percent is one meter two meters thick
幾成是一米兩米這麼厚
Then build a house on it and do all kinds of stuff
然後在上面蓋房子做各種東西
If the children grow up and want to separate
假如孩子長大了要分家的時候
It's the turf not the soil
它就這個草皮不是土皮
sod cut
草皮割掉
It's a separation
就是分家
formal separation
正式分家
what about this
那麼這個呢
just about
就是差不多是就是說
The origin of this potato
這個Potato的原產地
So
那麼
A few years ago we went to Match of Pitch
幾年前我們到Match of Pitch
this is very nice
這個是非常很好看的
It is said that in these places
據說在這些地方
Counted more than 2000 people
數了2000多個人
What do they say is Potato
他們說什麼是Potato
Mainly Potato
主要是Potato
Where is the potato planted?
Potato種在哪裡呢
planted here
種在這邊
I didn't find anything
我沒有把東西找出來
But the area here is not too big
不過這邊面積並不太大
But it can support 2000 people
不過能夠養2000個人
is quite productive quite high
是相當的生產力相當高
Then learn this little biology
那麼學這個生物學的小的
say something
假如說一個東西
place of origin
原產的地方
on average a lot
就平均就很多
average less words
平均少的話
For example, the European race
比如說歐洲的人種
Yes, there are fewer types
是種類是比較少一點
Africa is more
非洲是比較多一點
Because Africa is native
因為非洲是原產
Potato, Patata, Patata
那麼Potato, Patata, Patata
this can sometimes be confusing
這個有時候會混亂
For example, in the early
比如說在早期的
spanish
西班牙語
or italian
或者是義大利語
I often confuse Potato with sheep feathers
是从常常把Potato跟羊羽搞混了
But in Cretia are these people
不过 in Cretia 是这些人
These people in Mordaishu right here in England
就在英加利国的莫代书的这些人
Their language is called Cretia
他们的语言叫做Cretia
It translates sweet potato as
它把 sweet potato 翻译叫做
Bada in Taiwanese
台语有巴达
Potato called Bada
Potato叫巴达
So the Spaniards confuse the two powders
所以西班牙人就把这两个粉搞混了
Potato
就Potato
So early records
所以早期的记载
You have to be careful
你要小心
Sometimes they speak Potato
有时候他们是讲Potato
But honestly Sweet Potato
不过说实说 Sweet Potato
There is also the progress of the above
有上文的进行也有
So
那么
How should Potato be pronounced?
那应该Potato怎么念呢
what about this
这个呢
I want everyone to listen
我要让大家听
Tomato, let's call the old thing off.
Tomato, let's call the old thing off.
I just heard that the famous Armstrong and Inia Fitzgerald
剛才聽到的是很有名的Armstrong跟Inia Fitzgerald這樣
so this is very interesting
所以這個是很很有趣的
So it should be Potato, Patata, nothing.
所以應該講Potato, Patata, nothing.
Let’s talk about Potato production
再講Potato產量
If we talk about medium output, it is usually China
假如說中產量的話,常常是中國在手
But India and the Soviet Union are pretty good
不過印度蘇聯都相當不錯
you'll see later
等一下會看得到
If we look at it per capita, it is not China
假如說人均來看的話,並不是中國
Beyer, Indian Kiss, Russia, Baspeia, Poland, Russia, etc.
是拜爾、印度基斯、俄國、巴斯比亞、波蘭、俄國等等
Such as Bolivia, Mexico, and France
比如 Bolivia, Mexico, and France
very funny
很有趣
but anyway
不过反正
It can be seen that these countries can accept new crops from the New World
就可见这些国家能够接受新大陆的新作物
Taiwan too
台湾也是
Look at Yin Yang again
再看银杨
do i want to talk
我要不要详谈
because everyone knows
因为大家都知道
Anyway, Poleto is quite silver value
反正Poleto也是相当银杨价值
is quite high
是相当高的
Especially the protein is a little higher than this meal
尤其蛋白质比这个饭数比较高一点
There are also various hygienic
各种卫生素也有
Except Sanitin A
除了卫生素A以外
Everything else is pretty good
其他东西都相当很好
words in america
在美国的话
Often eat baked merry meringue
常吃烤玫瑞酥皮
The skin is actually delicious
皮其实很好吃
Its silver price is compared with the whole Poleto
它的银杨价值跟整个Poleto比起来
is also uncomfortable
也是不适
the good thing is
好的是
It's just that the skin is worth more
就是皮里头价值比较多一点
This is pretty good in terms of real nutrition
這個真正的營養來講是相當好
and delicious
而且好吃
have a big problem
有一個大問題
that is to say, what I just said
就是說我剛剛講到
we may not have talked
我們也許還沒講到
Grape fruit can be produced for a long time
葡萄果能夠出產了很久
several months
好幾個月
sometimes you see it sprout
有時候你會看到它發芽
If it sprouts, it's best to throw it away
發芽的話最要是把它扔掉
Because after germination, there is this
因為發芽以後這裡頭有這個
Solan Lin
所謂索蘭林
nongine
就是農會鹼
it's poisonous
這是很毒的
So in the past, grapes were more expensive
所以以前是葡萄果比較貴的時候
you just cut it off
你就把它切掉
but still not sure
不過還是切不清楚
so grape fruit is very cheap now
所以現在葡萄果非常便宜
so you can farm
所以您可農掉
Don't go for surgery again
不要去再次就做外科手術
then the question
那麼這個問題
I'm not a doctor either
我也不是醫生
But that's a lot of problems
不過這是很多很多毛病的
If the method of serious illness will be lost
假如重症的方法會失掉
So this is a big disadvantage
所以這個是一個大缺點
So what about the aborigines?
那麼所謂原住民呢
How to deal with marinsu for storage
怎麼樣處理馬林蘇來儲存呢
It has a thing called Tunno
它有一個一種東西叫做Tunno
this thing is wonderful
這個東西非常妙
Because Potato is mainly in
因為Potato主要是在
place of the anders plateau
安德斯高原的地方
it is very hot during the day
白天是很熱
it's cold at night
夜間是很冷
So put the potato out
所以把Potato放在外頭
freeze it
把它冰凍起來
Then step on it during the day
然後白天就用腳踩
just roll out the water
就把水分擀出來
If you do this kind of work for two or three days
做這個兩三天這種工作的話
Become a Tunno
變成Tunno
This is this small piece of Potato that was originally a relatively large piece
這是這小塊本來就是比較大塊的Potato
After doing this, it is a natural biscuit
這樣做了以後就是自然的冰乾
later can
以後可以
It is said that the two or three years of early spring collection
初春集兩三年據說
And after soaking in water
而且這個泡了水以後
still quite tasty
還是相當好吃
I haven't been out, I've seen
我是沒出過 我看過
So if sweet vegetables are compared with potatoes
那麼甘蔬跟馬鈴薯比較的話
Everyone knows this
這個大家也曉得
Sweets and vegetables prefer to be wet
甘蔬比較喜歡比較濕
clear weather
天氣清高的
not potatoes
馬鈴薯就不行
As long as it contains energy
只要含有能的地方可以
then just saw
那麼剛才已經看到
Ye Qing can
葉子菁都可以
I also saw that the leaf buds are poisonous
也看到葉芽都有毒
Sweets and Vegetables Compared to Potatoes
甘蔬比馬鈴薯比起來
It's just Jiuchun
是不過九純
this can last a long time
這是可以存了很久
It's fine for a few months
幾個月是沒問題
inverse value method
反值的方法
Sweets and Vegetables are Nakato
甘蔬就是中藤
I've hit it several times
我也中過好幾次
When i was young
在我小時候
This is Nakato faster
這個是中藤更快
Sweets and vegetables are not less
甘蔬比較沒出少
Because it crawls on the ground very quickly
因為它是在地上爬的很快很快
so can't let
所以不能夠讓
This weed grows out
這個渣草長出來
Malinsu needs Ecstasy longifolia
馬林蘇就需要長曙草
I have already said that Vitamin A is higher
我已經講過Vatamin A這個比較高一點
so often
那麼常常呢
Crop efficiency is compared in terms of heat
作物的效率是用熱量來比較
So the sweet potato marinsu just mentioned
所以剛才講的番薯馬林蘇
We didn't even talk about rice taro
我們也沒講到水稻芋
This is not from the Protestants
這個不是大新教徒來的
neither taro nor pony
芋頭也不是 小馬也不是
but do this
不過做這個
Just watch this first
你先只看這個好了
This statistic averages eight years
這個統計平均八年
Statistics made by Japanese agricultural students
日本農學生做的統計
what about sweet potatoes
那麼番薯呢
The heat generated by ten projects is so much
十個工程產生出來的熱量是這麼多
What about Malinsu?
那麼馬林蘇呢
A bit lower but pretty good
比較低一點 不過相當好
So it's lower
所以倒是低一點
but to understand
不過呢 要了解
Rice planting in Japan can only be done for one period
日本種水稻只能做一期
In Taiwan, there are two phases and three phases
在台灣是種兩期三期的
It should be a little more than this
這個照道理應該是比這個多一點
But anyway, this sweet potato
不過反正這個番薯呢
When this caloric standpoint
當這個熱量的立場來看呢
It is the most efficient of this crop
它是最高效率的這個作物
Wheat is better than this universe
比這個宇宙的小麥都是很好
Now let's talk about this corn
那現在呢我們講到這個玉米
Pan wheat
番麥
In the United States, English is often spoken in Korn
英語在美國的話呢常講Korn
Korn isn't actually a good name for this corn
Korn其實並不是這個玉米的好名聲
Korn originally means small particles in English
Korn本來在英語裡都是小顆粒的意思
so what
所以呢
Is it right that this corn is called Korn
這個玉米叫做Korn是不是很對的
in other countries
在其他的國家
It's the same English-speaking British word.
就是同樣的講英語的英國的話呢
They use Maze
他們就用Maze
This is from the scientific name
這是從學名
The scientific name also comes from here
學名也是從這裡來
So Zia Maze
所以Zia Maze
This corn was also fumigated many years ago
這個玉米也是很多年以前被熏化
So now you can see many kinds of
那麼現在去也是能夠看到很多種
Three or four years ago when I went
我去的時候三四年前
The ones they most often come up with are shorter
他們最常拿出來的是比較短的
Not enough corn with large grains
而不夠顆粒很大的玉米
came out very tasty
出來非常好吃
So now that's a lot
所以現在就是這個很多
But also see many kinds of
不過也看到很多很多種的
there is a disadvantage
有個缺點呢
because there is a shortcoming
因為有個缺點
is it missing something
是它缺少某些東西
The first one is Vitamin B3
第一個就是Vitamin B3
This is called Ni-Syn
這個叫做Ni-Syn
No-Syn
Ingen-Syn
this thing should be
這個東西是應該
Use alkaline water to get the oil out
要用鹼水才能夠把它油理出來
without this
沒有這個的話
This Pelagra can happen again
又可以發生這個Pelagra
this is lack
這個就是缺乏
That is, weight loss and physical strength will decrease
就是體重會減少,體力會降低
In addition, cut less chestnut acid and sian acid in the corn
另外,玉米里頭切少栗酸跟斯安酸
this is very important
這個是非常要緊的事情
But fortunately, you can supplement these two amino acids by eating beans
不過幸虧你吃豆類可以把補給這兩個安基酸
Finally, we will talk about beans from the New World.
最後會講到新大陸的豆類
like going to a mexican restaurant
比如說到墨西哥餐館的話
You often see beans come out with corn
你常看到豆跟玉米一起出來的
all make sense
都是有道理的
We talked about the word waxy
我們講到糯一個字
Everyone likes glutinous rice, and also likes brown rice
大家喜歡的糯米,也喜歡的糙米
So, does glutinous rice have glutinous rice?
那麼,糯米有沒有糯米呢?
yes, where
是有,哪裡有
There was once a time when Nuo corn was discovered in mainland China
本來現在曾經有一次諾玉米在中國大陸發現
So China's Scientology is very happy
所以中國的科學教就非常高興
we also have the origin of corn
我們也有玉米的原產地
But then I realized it wasn't
不過後來就曉得並不是
But let's talk about Nomi Chaomi first
不過先講諾米超米
I'll tell you a little deeper knowledge
我就給你講一點深化的知識
This is the test of knowledge
這是知識相驗
So you should try this
所以你們應該想驗這個
some people
有些人
I should talk about this first
我應該先講這個在座的
There are many experts here
有很多專家在這裡
I'm really taking the liberty to say these things
我實在是冒昧講這些東西
But I'm more of an expert on this
不過這項我是比較專科
So obsessive electric mixer is like this
所以執念的電混是這樣
So the obsessed electric mixer is like this
那麼執念的電混是這樣
This is called Amylose Amylopectin like this
這個叫做Amylose Amylopectin這樣子
then the year does matter
那麼年度是有關係
It's probably conceivable
這樣子大概可以想像
it is very sticky
它是非常黏黏的
It's not sticky and simple
這就不黏黏單純
Therefore, there are fewer obsessive electric lines in glutinous rice
所以執念電紋在糯米裡比較少
Aminopectin
不過Aminopectin
There are many, many electric lines of obsession
執念電紋在這裡很多很多
so normal this
那麼平常的這個
It is usually in the case of brown rice
就是平常在糙米的話
mostly
多半都是
Most of them are electric lines of obsession
大部分就是執念的電紋
Then the electric lines of obsession are less
那麼執念的電紋是比較少一點
The glutinous rice just mentioned is now
剛才講的糯米現在
Although originally discovered in China
雖然是原先在中國發現
but already
不過已經是
Glutinous rice goes to America
糯米到美大陸去
Now almost the world's
現在差不多世界上的這個
The so-called glutinous rice electric pattern is
所謂糯米電紋都是
so-called glutinous rice
所謂糯米來的
Well this has been said and dance
那麼這個已經講過了就跳舞
by the way
順便
Let me tell you about the glycemic index
跟大家講這個生糖指數
You can't talk about calories in food
你對食物不能夠光講熱量
It also depends on how the heat is absorbed by ourselves
也看熱量怎麼被我們自己來吸收
some
有的呢
our reason
我們事來由
blood sugar rises rapidly
血糖就很快的增加
speak slowly
慢慢的講說
some
有的呢
just increase slowly
就是慢慢增加
And you can't use this weight to calculate
而且你不能夠用這個重量來算
So you should use this glycemic index to see
所以應該用這個生糖指數來看
Well of course I won't go into details
那麼當然我不會講詳細的事情
but
不過
White rice and grass rice
白飯白米跟草米
You can see it by comparing
你就比起來就可以看得出來
some things are the same
有的東西同樣一個
total calories are the same
總熱量是一樣的
The glycemic index is so different
生糖指數就太不一樣了
so what
所以呢
The tallest is French bread
最高的就是法國麵包
Baguette is the highest
Baguette是最高
So people who like to eat French bread be careful
所以喜歡吃法國麵包的人要小心一點
I won’t talk about it, I don’t want to talk about it, you read a lot of such records on the Internet
我就不講,不想去講,這個你在網路上看很多很多這種記載
Then the third thing I want to talk about is the so-called Banyok
那麼第三個東西我要講的是所謂Banyok
Banyok is probably Cassava in Taiwan.
Banyok在台灣大概是Cassava這種話比較用得多
Yoga, or yoga is the same
Yoga,或者是Yoga都是一樣的
Cassava is 木薯、樹薯
Manyok就是木薯、樹薯
Our common ones are potato flour or Taipei flour.
我們常見的就是薯薯粉或者台北粉
In fact, the glutinous rice just mentioned is often mixed to make Taipei flour.
其實剛才講的糯米常常是把它拌做台北粉
But because it becomes very sticky after heating it up a little
不過因為放了以後就稍微加熱一下就變成非常黏
this is taipei powder
這是台北粉
So the glutinous rice just mentioned is also Taipei flour.
所以剛才講的糯米也是台北粉
It is also the third largest crop in the world
也是世界第三大的作物
Mainly not in the US
主要的不是在美国
and mainly in Africa
而且主要是在非洲
Tapioca that can be mainly seen now
现在主要可以看到的Tapioca
There is a spherical Tapioca
有一种球状的Tapioca
Making Tapioca Balls
做球状的Tapioca
i don't have time to talk
我没有时间讲
what to say later
以后要指论的话
wait a minute i will talk too
等一下我也会讲
Also by Tapioca
也有靠Tapioca
There is also Tapioca made into balls
也有做球状的Tapioca
I have already mentioned
我已经讲到
Counting Electric Soul
数数电魂
The quality electric soul is a little more
质量电魂比较多一点
So would be able to make this
所以会能够做成这个
good
好
So
那么
This thing Tapioca also has toxins
这个东西Tapioca也有毒素
Also inside the rooting or quick-rooting bark
也在生根或者快根皮里头
glycoside
有产生青酸配糖脂
Green acid is
青酸就是
when everyone wants to commit suicide
大家想要自杀的时候
just eat this
就是吃这个
But I didn't finish half of what I just said.
不過我剛才講了一半沒有講完
That is to say, this Tapioca is very important in Africa
就是說這個Tapioca是在非洲是非常重要
The main reason is that those places in Africa do not have enough water
主要就是說非洲那些地方水分不夠
You can't grow sweet potatoes, but you can grow them
不能夠種番薯 種的是可以
but not too successful
不過不會太成功
Then grow this Tapioca
那麼種這個Tapioca
The local people of the Tapioca people are very active
那麼種Tapioca人的地方人都很非常激活
So it can't wait to dig out the root and eat it
所以它就等不得把這個根成熟挖出來就吃了
so the problem is big
所以問題就很大
The problem is that it's not mature enough to take root
問題就是說它還沒有成熟的生根
It just doesn't grow roots
就是並不是生長出根來
It is the unripe root, the root block
就是還沒有熟的根 根塊
After eating it, it will produce green acid
拿來吃的以後它就產生青酸
Anyone who knows a little chemistry can see that
要懂得一點化學的人就可以看得出來
This is the source of cyanic acid
這是青酸的來源
this is a big problem
這個是很大的問題
then we will soon
那麼我們很快
is there any time here
這裡有沒有時間
time comparison
時間比較
Tomato
Tomato
Tomato is another Solannam
Tomato又是一個Solannam
I bind the peril
Ligo pericum
Ligo is
Ligo是
Long
Long
Pericum is peach
Pericum是peach
Tao
Tao
This is from
這是來自於
Mexico B. Lu Gaudi
Mexico B. Lu Gaudi
This should read B
這個應該是念B
this country
這個國家
before
以前也
Once became B Lu by himself
曾經自己成為B Lu
Not Peru
不是Peru
This is
這是
marjoram
Majoran
go to the philippines
到菲律賓去
Then what
然後呢
Just isolate
就隔離
spread very fast
傳播得很快很快
imagine this now
大家現在想像這個
to an italian restaurant
到意大利餐館去
no escape
沒有絕對逃不掉
Before going to the museum
去館前
not italian
不是意大利館餐的
often in usa
常常在美國
work
上班
The question is, is it a fruit or a vegetable?
有这个讨论就是到底是水果还是蔬菜呢
Both fruits and vegetables are good and nutritious
不管是水果还是蔬菜也很好是很有营养
so what is
那么什么是
So this is from Tomato
那么这个呢是 Tomato 的
the origin of this phrase
这个一句词的来源
Asthex is called Citomato
Asthex 叫做 Citomato
What about the rest of Central America?
那么其他的中美洲呢
Just get rid of this first Ciraba
就把这个头一个Ciraba弄掉
Screaming Tomato
叫 Tomato
Then when you go to Australia or Italy?
然后呢到澳洲到意大利的时候呢
don't use this
并不用这个
It's called Pomodoro
它叫 Pomodoro
Pomo means Apple
Pomo 就是苹果的意思
Doro is gold
Doro 就是金色
golden apple
金色的苹果
Then the discourse is called Pom de Moll
那么话语叫 Pom de Moll
What about this? Actually, if you say
这个呢其实你假如说
If it is directly released, it is the apple of love
直接放异的话呢就是爱情的苹果
But it has nothing to do with love
不过其实它跟爱情没有关系
you love
你对情
Ask someone to eat this apple and it won't love you more
请人拿这个苹果吃它不会更加爱你
It is said that the document I read recently said this
据说我最近看的这个文献上面是讲这么讲
This one originally meant this Pom de Mour
这个呢 本来是指这个Pom de Mour
It's the Mu'er people, the people in northern Africa.
就是沐儿人 非洲的北部的这个人
What about these people, just call this eggplant this
这些人呢 就把这个茄子叫这个
France is anti-made this called Pom de Mour
法国就是防造这个 叫做Pom de Mour
So don't give your lover too much Tomato
所以不要给你的情人太多的Tomato吃
what about when i go somewhere else
那么我到别路去的时候呢
only see this thing
只能看见这个东西
tomato on tree
番茄生在树上
Then Taiwan also has
那么台湾也有
not native is there
不是原产是在那里
yes yes
对 是啊
So this thing is
所以呢 这个东西是
Actually, it's the tomato tree
其实说起来是这个番茄树
I ate several of them and they were pretty good, just like the usual fairy tales
我吃了好几个,相当好,跟平常的童话都是一模一样的
Well, of course, the ingredients in the tomato are only quite good, that is, the soup is a little less
那么当然,番茄里头的用源只是相当好,就是汤汁比较少一点
The water side is also a little less, but the taste is quite high
水方也少一点,但味道相当高
And this is the medium production of China, the United States, Turkey, India, etc.
而且这个是中产量的中国,美国,土耳其,印度等等
In terms of crowds, these numbers are different
就说用人群的话,这些数字就不一样
However, the most important source of use in tomatoes is a product, which is lycopene
不过番茄里头最重要的用源就是来个品,这是番茄红素
It is a major anti-oxygen antioxidant
这是一个主要的 anti-oxygen 抗氧化剂
Then also the predecessor of this carotenoid
那么也是这个 carotenoid 的前身
So, Tomato is a tomato that has quite a different value
所以, Tomato 是番茄是相当有异样的价值
We don't need to talk about this anymore
这个我们就不用再讲了
What I want to tell you is
要講給大家聽的就是
Holidays can leave the release of Tomato Flavor Elements
假日可以出境番茄風素的釋放
Then look at the next one
那麼就看下面一個
But this first
不過這個先一個
one
一個
Interjection is to say that the United States is said
插話就是說美國屬上說
If your dog is sprayed by this shy boy
假如你的狗被這個羞幼噴來幼
it stinks very stinky
它很臭很臭的
Can't be washed off with flying photos
用飛照都洗不掉
so what to do
那麼怎麼辦呢
They just say use this
他們就是說用這個
tomato
Tomato來洗
Tomato Juice to wash
Tomato Juice來洗
Because of the lake bottle thing
因為萊克瓶這個東西
is polyunsaturated
是多不飽和的
It's hard to live
都不好活
So the smelly thing it sprays out is called
所以它噴出來的這個臭的東西是叫做
Milk Captain
Milk Captain
So it can be quickly absorbed by this hair
所以能夠被這個發物很快地吸收
But let's be honest
不過這說實這麼說
You don't have to commit a crime when you take your dog out in the wild
你帶狗在野外走的時候不一定有犯
guilty and beside
犯且在旁邊
so to be honest
所以說實這麼說
So it's better to fight with small trees
所以最好還是用小樹打
Add this peroxide core
跟加這個過氧化芯
Then it will be fine after oxidation.
那麼氧化了以後就不錯了
good
好
Well, half of what I just said
那麼剛才講到講一半
It is only when Lycopin is heated that it can be released
就是萊克品加熱才能夠釋放
This is when there is no heat
這個就是沒有加熱的時候
It becomes brighter after heating
這樣加熱以後變亮
So after heating it releases
所以加熱以後就釋放
Then there is a simultaneous experiment
那麼有一個同時進行的實驗
Do Vitamin C Thoroughly
做Vitamin C的徹底
Vitamin C is not as fragile as everyone thinks
Vitamin C並不大家所想像的那麼脆弱
It goes through 80 degrees is 30 minutes at least -1
它經過80度是30分鐘至少-1
20 percent only
20個percent而已
So it doesn't hurt too much
所以並不會損害太多
However, during this period, the Lai Kepin has increased a lot
不過期間這個賴克品就增加了很多了
The function of this Lai Kepin is quite good
這個賴克品的功能是相當好
Mainly sunscreen
主要是抗陽光劑
And its active strength is 10 times stronger than Vitamin E
而且它的活性強度比Vitamin E的10倍
Twice as much as Kyler's Note so pretty good
跟Kyler's Note的2倍所以相當好
So love or not, you can eat more of this
所以愛情不愛情你可以多吃這個
ease
緩解
Well, maybe you think this
那麼這個也許大家覺得
Catchup is used
用的叫Catchup
In kyogen, the word looks like this
这个字用狂言来讲很像这个
right
对不对
This is the catchup could be this
这是Catchup的可能是这个
then come back
那么再回过来讲
Peanuts
Peanuts
occur
发生
I prefer to fall
我是比较喜欢落发生
the intention to lose it when it happens
发生就失去它的这个一分来的意向
Ditto is ok
地斗还可以
Longevity Fruit Too Severe and Deep Imperial Physician
长生果实太严深的太医
The imperial doctor's dirt bucket and wide bucket can do it
太医那个土斗宽斗都可以
In Japanese it is called Tang Ren Dou
日语里头叫把它叫做唐人斗
Nanjing bucket
南京斗
is to indicate its source
是表示它的来源
it is imported from china
它是从中国输进来
That's why it's called Tangrendou
所以叫做唐人斗
Nanjing bucket
南京斗
Then look at this seed
那么再看这个种料
The production volume is still China's No. 1 in India, etc., etc.
生产量还是中国第一印度等等等等等等
so
所以
In fact, Taiwanese pronunciation is quite natural.
其實台語的發聲是相當好自的
more vocal than other countries
比其他的國家的發聲
i think so
我是覺得是這樣
The spoken word is also
發聲的語詞也是
Spaniards are closer to earthfish
西班牙人比較靠近土魚
like chili
像是辣椒
it's still called chili
它還是叫辣椒
Spain is called Wette
西班牙就叫做Wette
Germany is called Archnus
德國是叫做Archnus
bean of soil
就是土的豆
Of course it doesn't make sense for me to mention this
當然這個我沒有意義舉出來
with italian etc.
跟意大利文等等
German and Dutch etc are two systems
德國和荷蘭人等等都是兩個系統
whatever you call it
不管你怎麼叫
vocalization is very
發聲是非常
very high volume
音量之非常高
Where is the height?
高在什麼地方呢
Because the heat is not too high
因為熱量並不太高
The heat of the fire rice comes from the main body and from the main yellow
火飯的熱量是來自主 而且來自主黃
Soup is not high
湯汁也不高
1,000 yuan for a pig is a bit higher
豬一千塊比較高一點
then the protein is very high
那麼蛋白質非常高
And this one has very, very high offshore acid
這個呢 而且的非常有非常高的離岸酸
So you eat corn best with
所以你吃玉米最好是用
peanuts to cultivate
花生來培養
So you can make up this offshore acid
所以就可以補這個離岸酸
Then these various
那麼這些各種各樣的
it is enough
這是要足夠的
So let's talk about this
那麼我們就來講這個
Fanshiliu
番石流
guava
芭樂
what about this
這個呢
its origin is not clear
它的原產地並不明確
Because very early on it was
因為很早它就從
probably from
大概是從
Into the Americas from southern Mexico
墨西哥南部傳入住美洲
Then what
然後呢
the entire interior of the Americas
整個美洲的內地區
with the West Indies, etc.
跟西印度的群島等等
islands are
島嶼都就是
Guo Lunbu hasn't entered yet
郭倫布還沒進
It has spread a little bit before reaching the U.S.
到美國以前就已經傳播了一點
then of course
然後當然
maybe not later
可能不一來以後
spread more widely
更加傳播的更廣
So
那麼
This is Spread Before Columbus
這個就是 Spread Before Columbus
then this
那麼這個
this
這個
What about Leo's name?
凡是利歐的名字呢
Celium Guajaba
Celium Guajaba
Reflected in Spanish
反映在 Spanish
spanish french
西班牙語 法國
All use this Guajaba
都是用這種 Guajaba
GU A-Handle-Hanging Art
Gua-ba-guayate
wait wait wait wait
等等等等等等
So why is Taiwan called Bala?
那麼台灣為什麼叫Bala
I don't have this yet
這個我還沒有
full of explanations
有滿滿的解釋
The advanced possibilities of everyone here
各位在座的先進可能
will teach me
會指教我
why this
為什麼這個
Bala in Taiwan
台灣的Bala
where did i come from
我以前是從哪裡來
So the world's
所以世界各國的這個
None of this
都沒有這種
The difference is
比較不一樣的就是
Abbas of Guam
關島的 Abbas
it's quite different
這是比較不一樣
Nothing like this one in Bala
沒有相近這個Bala的這個
the noun
這個名詞
good
好
Look at its nutritional value
再看它的營養價值
not too hot
熱量並不太高
The wind is not too high
水風也不太高
fiber is a lot
纖維是很多
But the microphone is also quite impressive
但麥克風也相當可觀
A wide variety of sanitation is good
各種各樣的衛生素是很好
But the best thing is
不過最好的好處就是
Bitem is very high
Bitem is very high
So
那麼
Plus things like Baili
外加百里這種東西
It is said
據說
According to this document
據這個文獻來講
is very functional
是非常有功能
that's what they say
就是他們說
common sense barra can lower
常識巴拉可以降低
type 2 diabetes
第二型的糖尿病
So Taiwan has four seasons
那麼台灣是一年四季
All produce this Fanshiliu
都產這個藩石流
output is large
產量是大
According to my guess, there are few in the whole country
我據我猜想是全國有數的
so what
所以呢
All Barra water is good
都是巴拉水很好
also have problems
也有毛病
But needless to say
不過不用講
Well, I've probably already said this
好 這個我大概已經講過了
One thing I also pointed out is that
有一點我也指出來的就是
Way stream leaves are also very useful
方式流的葉子也非常有用
It's probably not like before when we went to the country when we were kids
現在大概沒有以前我們小時候到鄉下去的時候
He sees this way the leaves that flow into tea attack women
他看這個方式流的葉子弄成茶攻擊女人
So this is a very generous kind of thing
所以這個是非常慷慨的一種東西
I probably don't have such a good thing now
我現在大概是沒有這麼好的事情
This can be seen look at this
這個可以看來看這個
Bai Lamin is one person equal to three oranges
白臘民是一個人等於是三個橘子
Sometimes three oranges are too much to eat
三個橘子有時候是吃不下的
Then just eat one and eat one spicy enough
然後就吃一個吃一個把辣就夠了
Talk about this square sauce chili
講這個方醬子辣椒
Chili is also eaten quite early
辣椒也是相當早的時候就吃了
It turned out that the remixing started in Beijing
原来是在北京开始再配
it was in the southwest
原来是在西南部
It is said so
据说是这样
The ship also passes through the Philippines and India
船路也是经过菲律宾、印度
Then in China, Indonesia, Korea, Japan
然后在中国、印尼、韩国、日本这样
The engineering department also brought directly to Spain, Fortaur
工程部也直接带到西班牙、佛陶尔
This pepper can be divided into three types
这个椒可以分成三种
Green Peppers, Chili Peppers, Chili Peppers
青椒、天椒、辣椒
The reason for this spiciness is a substance called capsaicin
这个辣的原因是一个叫辣椒素
capsaicin
辣椒素,capicin
This is actually in medicine now
这个其实现在也在医药
You can also use this
也可以用这个
When doing this various medicine
当在做这个各医的时候
There must be several doctors who can confirm this
一定要有几个医生可以证实这个
have a good one
有一个好去的
there are birds
有去的是鸟类
just lacking on this chili
就缺乏对这个辣椒
But the birds are not spicy when they eat these things
可是鸟类吃这些东西就不辣
Of course it doesn't matter
当然还没有关系
why i don't know
为什么我也不曉得
I don't know why there is any advantage
为什么有什么优点我也不曉得
Beef is not spicy
牛肉就不吃辣不辣
then the next thing is very interesting
那么下一个东西是非常有趣
And the story of its origin goes like this
而且它的来源的故事是这样
Not a soil genus for a deficiency
不是一个土属的一个不足
then you can also see
那么你们也可以看得出来
It's not easy for mortals to fall in love
不容易凡人相恋的
But the princess fell in love with this handsome
然而公主爱上这个俊美
Of course the one who falls in love must be handsome
当然爱上的一定是俊美
Probably not feed it Tomato
可能不是给它吃 Tomato
Then this pair of relatives escaped from their father's arrest
那么这个一对亲人就逃避父亲的罪捕
This is often a myth or an old story
这个常常神话或者是老故事常有
This is very cruel
这个非常残忍的就是说
they were arrested inside tropical sage
他们在热带圣人里头被捕
And be beheaded
而且当上斩首
this is very cruel
这是非常残忍的
Then their seats stay on the ground
那么他们的学座留在地上
become this thing
变成这个玩意
This is Vanilla's story
这是Vanilla的故事
This is where Vanilla comes from
这就是Vanilla的来源
There are of course stories like this everywhere.
类似这种故事当然各地都有
This is a story of Vanilla
这是Vanilla的一个故事
Vanilla's wind walk is also a bit weird
Vanilla的风步也比较怪一点
Because it's not China anymore
因为现在不是中国了
not america
也不是美国
Vanilla is a country
Vanilla is a country
China also has it, but I have big ideas
中国也有不过我想法很大很大
Mexico etc.
墨西哥等等
Because what Vanilla found was a French doctor
因为Vanilla发现的是一个法国医生
French doctors later transplanted him to
法国医生后来就把他移植到
an island in a certain french pavilion
某一个法国馆的一个岛屿
later planted
后来种了以后
The plant is growing
种植物是长起来了
But it won't be able to receive
不过不会不能够收
I said that Vanilla just talked about it
我说过到这个Vanilla刚才讲
The things I saw just now can't grow
刚才看的这些东西长不出来
later they found out
后来他们发现
One of their efforts compared to a very smart effort
他们的一个努力比较很聪明的努力
i think he found out
我想他发现
because there is no
因为那个地方没有
There is no certain wind to medium this hair powder
没有某一种风来媒介这个发粉
Later this clever effort
后来这个很聪明的努力就
invented this so-called artificial pollination method
发明这个所谓人工受粉的方法
To be able to deliver this vanilla up
才能够把这个Vanilla送起来
able to be strong
能够结实
So he won't be the one you normally see
所以他不会是在平常你看到的
Compared with the crispy corn, there are more residual crispy
玉米和放酥的比较残酥比较多的
then this i like very much
那么这个我非常喜欢
I ask the source of this corn
我求这个玉米的来源
What about the term Vanilla?
Vanilla这个名词呢
It was only in 1989 that there was this Barneyland
是1989年才有这个百尼兰
This is from Barneyland
这个是从百尼兰
Baccarat
就是百家尔兰
latin is parnylan
拉丁就是百尼兰
It's Xiaolizi
就是小里子
One very important thing is
有一个很重要的就是
Flavor after fermentation
发酵以后才有香味
there is no way you put it there
你放在那里就是没有办法
It must be treated in some way to have a scent
一定要经过某种处理才能够有香味
what's inside benylon
百尼兰里头呢
There is a direction, this join has fermentation technology
有方向这个加入有发酵技术
can see this
可以看得出来这个
Pippi and Marilyn
皮皮尿酪跟玛莉琳
Marilyn sometimes this is called a candy
玛莉琳有时候这个另外叫一个糖
so what
所以呢
These two are the most important direction components
这两个是最重要的方向成分
So
那么
So now about this chocolate
那么现在谈到这个巧克力
chocolate
巧克力
chocolate this
巧克力这个
This number is called
这个数字里面叫
Til Brown Mocha High
蒂尔布朗摩卡高
Thiel is a god
蒂尔就是神
Bronmore is food
布朗摩就是食物
water of god
就是神的水
In fact, they often eat this chocolate in the king of aspen juice, for example.
真正他们在比如说阿斯汁的王也常吃这个巧克力
he doesn't eat this chocolate
他并不是吃这种巧克力
They eat the thick jelly of this tissue
他们把这个组织很浓的胶质来吃
This is about 1100
这个是差不多1100年
Said relatively new discovery
说比较新的发现
It was produced by China and the United States
就是中美产生出来的
here are black and white chocolate
这里有黑跟白的巧克力
White chocolate is not real chocolate
白巧克力并不是真正的巧克力
why
为什么呢
because it is not without this chocolate
因为它不是不含这个巧克力的
what i told you just now
刚才我给你讲的那个东西
so chocolate has several things
所以巧克力有几种东西
so very important
所以很重要
this is the most important
这个是最重要
Fanel et alamin
Fanel et alamin
Fanis
Fanis安
This thing is a neural address
这个东西是一个神经地址
This means you feel good and comfortable after eating it
这个就是吃来以后你就觉得很好很舒服
so you don't have to send this tomato
所以你不用送这个番茄
send some chocolate
送巧克力套一点
There is also this Theodore Bramins
另外也有这个Theodore Bramins
This is very similar to caffeine
这个跟咖啡因是非常类似
The difference is this place
相差就是这个地方
There is this clip machine in the coffee
咖啡里头是有这个夹机
not here
这里就没有
It's not important that its function is almost the same
不主要的它的功能是差不多一样的
So white chocolate doesn't have those things
所以白巧克力就没有这些东西
So your white chocolate is free
所以你白巧克力就是白送
Not only free gift but also harm
不但是白送还做害
why do harm
为什么做害呢
Because it contains Coconut Butter
因为里头含有是Coconut Butter
cheese
乳酪
Fukalabada is all about saturated food
福卡拉巴达就是有饱和的食物
too many nights
晚上太多了
so you send white chocolate
所以你送白巧克力
just want your lover to be early
就是要你的情人早点
having a heart attack etc.
犯心脏病等等
So give me a dark chocolate set
所以还是送黑巧克力套
Let's talk about beans
再讲豆类
Beans Actually Every Week in New World Beans
豆类其实每一周的新大陆的豆类
are more expensive than the rule of law in Russia
都贵于法治俄罗斯
lots and lots of beans
很多很多豆
Among them, there are many kinds of Taiwan
其中台湾也好多种在那里
For example, the rule of law Russia we call Kidney Bean
比如说我们叫菜豆的法治俄罗斯
Yellow Ground Bean Lemabini
黄地豆 莱马比尼
Lema is actually a
莱马这个东西其实是一个
In picture one is about the emperor
在图一是讲皇帝
Inge also means emperor
英格也是皇帝的意思
So this is what Emperor Bean means
所以这是皇帝豆的意思
It's all against
都是反的對
So this is a lot of land
所以是這個房地多
Many other beans are freshly poured in
其他有好多種豆都是新倒入來的
so i just said
所以我剛才講
If you eat corn, you must supplement it with beans.
吃玉米的話一定要豆類來補
In other words, you only need ten items on nutrition.
或者說你就營養就十條
Finally I talk about these plants
最後我講到這些植物
I'll start by telling you about the Fromosa Plants
我先告訴大家這一本佛羅莫薩植物
It was written by the priest Mr. Pan Fujun
是祭祀潘富俊先生寫的
This sign is inserted from his book
這個表示從他那本書插來
Well, what happened to the corn turned the book, actually I already talked about it
那麼玉米發生翻書翻實際我已經講到了
sleep
睡覺
Probably none of you didn't expect that you brought it to America with your own hands.
大概沒有大家沒想到是親手日帶美洲來的
papaya is also pineapple
木瓜也是鳳梨
I thought the pineapple was from Taiwan but it wasn't
我以為鳳梨是台灣的並不是
Pumpkin is not Freddie and certainly not cassava and neither
南瓜也不是房地多當然不是木薯也不是
Passion fruit is not strawberry nor is it
白香果也不是草莓也不是
look at its orchid garden
你看它的蘭園
In the early days, most of them passed through the Philippines
早期是多半是经过菲律宾
Of course it's not that simple
当然不是那么简单
But whenever we see, for example,
不过凡是比如说我们看到
also through the Philippines
也是经过菲律宾
It may also come via the mainland
也可能是经过大陆在来
Everything that comes from sleep is pretended
凡是由睡觉都是装回来的
Then papaya and so on are all troubles
那么木瓜等等都是发难发难
Closer means
比较近的就是说
The genus is from Brazil through the South Island of Southeast Asia
木属是从巴西经过南洋南岛
Baixiang fruit is brought by the Japanese
白香果是日本人带来
Strawberries are also brought by the Japanese
草莓也是日本人带来
But of course it's originally from the New World.
不过当然这是原来是从新大陆来的
so far we have only talked about plants
那么到现在所讲的只是植物
We are not partial to plants
我们并不是偏爱植物
But because most of the things from the New World
不过因为多半的新大陆来的东西
more plants
是比较植物多一点
Then you think about what kind of New World
那么你想想新大陆有哪一种
This animal can attack the Old World
這種動物可以攻擊舊大陸
including Taiwan
包括台灣
can you name a few
你們能不能舉出幾個
but food
不過是食物嗎
So animals don't move much food over there
所以動物從那邊移過來的食物並不太多
this
這個
This is also quite
這個是在美國也是相當
This is Shenzhen, a native of the United States
這是這個深圳是美國土產
Now there's this wildfire machine
現在還有這個野火機
Of course, now is the time for the so-called temperature-sensitive world
當然現在是所謂感溫界的時候
is a lot
是弄得很多的
then this
那麼這個
how come
怎麼能
The other is overturning
另外一个就是翻压
This is me a few months ago half a year ago
这是我几个月以前半年前
Overturned photos taken outside Ulu
在乌鲁外照的翻压的相
They still have pressure
他们还有翻压
I don't quite understand that winter progresses
我不太懂得是冬季进步的
I can't think of anything to do with this
我是想不出这个有什么补
It's weird to appear on the stage
出台面相比较怪以外
why i don't know
为什么补 我不曉得
Then only in this
那么这个里面就只能够
I experienced it myself
自己体会了
Sauce duck, honey duck, etc.
酱母鸭 蜂蜜鸭等等
So these two birds
所以这两种鸟类
just compare
就是比较
animal that produces more food
产量比较多的食物的动物
per continent per continent
每大陆 每受大陆
never looked like a cow
本来就没有像牛
Or animals like pigs don't have
或是猪那种动物没有
this is for many reasons
这个是很多原因
I don't have time to talk about that now
我现在也没有时间讲那些
some are some
有的有的是有的
then this is not food
那麼這個不是食物
But there is a very influential thing is tobacco
不過有一個非常影響很大的東西是煙草
I'll talk about this before I talk about tobacco
我講煙草以前先講這個
Solanan
前科的索拉南
A lot of this pig in this family is food
這一科的這個豬很多都是食物
So is Gou Ji
苟紀也是
Tobacco Of course many of these things belong to Solanan
煙草當然這些很多東西都是屬於索拉南
Tobacco belongs to this too
煙草也是屬於這個
Then everyone knows Nicotin
那麼尼克丁大家都曉得了
The impact of this tobacco is not only on Taiwan
這個煙草的影響不但是對台灣
Great influence all over the world
全世界都非常大的影響
not food
並不是食物
But the biggest impact
不過影響是最大
then when we were kids
那麼我們小時候
We went to learn that the digital product of Taiwan's main business is ABCSR
我們去學到台灣的主業的數字產物是ABCSR
very different now
现在大不一样
A is for anana
A是anana
This is Pineapple
这是Pinapple
dividend
红利
B is of course banana
B当然是banana
C is for elder
C是长老
Campfer
Campfer
S is of course sugar
S当然是sugar
R is for rice
R是rice
T
T
different now
现在都不一样
C may be computer
C可能是computer
Everyone didn't know for a while
大家一时期下都不曉得
Anyway, this is very different from now
反正这个跟现在是大不一样
So
那么
girls dating
女生来往
We Colombus
我们Colombus
provide us with many things
供给给我们很多东西
So what's coming back in Asia
那么亚洲有什么东西回进
First
第一个
The big thing is soybeans
大样的东西是黄豆
Soybeans are very very very high impact
黄豆是非常影响非常非常大
The other one is the duck
另外一个就是鸭子
Then I won't talk about the other one now
那么另外一个我现在不讲
I'll talk about it later
以后再讲
So let's talk about soybeans first
所以先讲这个黄豆
soybeans sleeping in england
黄豆在英国睡觉
Suo Yabing
索鸦冰
then in
那么在
America is Suo Yibing
美国是索一冰
soya ice
英国叫索鸦冰
in japanese
在日语
soy sauce is called soy sauce
酱油是叫做酱油
so what about this
所以这个呢
from
从
Soya ice comes from soy sauce
索鸦冰是从酱油来的
then the United States
那么美国就
The United States likes to put some things
美国都很喜欢把一些的东西
shorten
缩短
simplify
简化
Suo Yibing
索一冰
what about soybeans
那么黄豆呢
Of course you can make tofu
当然能够做豆腐
Soy sauce is also doing very well in the United States now
酱油现在在美国也做得很
Soybean oil
大豆油
Natto
纳豆
No
不
Natto everyone is also very popular in Taiwan
纳豆大家在台湾也很
often do things
常常做的东西
then there is soy sauce
那么也有酱油
So very popular in America
那么在美国非常流行
Elamame means
Elamame就是说
that is
就是
It's written in Japanese
日语写出来的就是
soy beans
酱油豆
So
那么
hygienic soup
卫生汤
Sanitary soup this time
这次卫生汤
then this is
那么这是
China passes through the UK
中国经过英国才到
to the United States
美国去的
Then soybean production
那么大豆的生产
America is thirty-five percent
美國是百分之三十五
brazil is twenty seven
巴西是二十七
argentina is nineteen
阿根廷是十九
China is less
中國呢反而少
so what
所以呢
this is an asian
這是一個亞洲
non into columbus one
非進哥倫布的一個
elephant
大象
So
那麼
Of course this
當然這個
Then tell another
那麼另外講一個
that is
就是說
peking duck
北京鴨
in the US is called
在美國是叫做
Nagashima duck
長島鴨
in America
在美國呢
duck just compare
鴨只是比較
the small one
小的這個
salary increase industry
加薪業
but
不過
Every year there are so many
每年有這麼多隻
of
的
chicken and turkey
雞跟火雞
Well, there are fewer ducks
那麼鴨呢比較少
but
不過
The main thing is more than 90 percent
主要的是百分之九十以上
it's long island duck
是長島鴨
Long Island is Long Island
長島就是Long Island
New York
紐約
like nearby
附近的那樣
looks like this
长得就是这样
It's exactly the same in Beijing
就是北京完全一样
So in fact someone said yes
所以其实有人说是
The Tang Island tooth in the United States is better than that in Beijing, China
美国的唐岛牙比在中国的北京还好
possible
可能
So this is about this tooth seed again
那么这个又是讲到这个牙籽
Yazi Beijing Ya is not actually Beijing
牙籽北京牙其实不是北京
Check it out
一查的话
it is nanjing tooth
它是南京牙
So there is a story
所以有个故事就是
Anyway, Beijing Dental
反正北京牙
After Nanjing Teeth became Beijing Teeth
南京牙变成北京牙以后
It was only in the hands of the Americans in the 1973 era
才被美国人一把七三年时代
Seven Beijing teeth go to the United States
七只的北京牙到美国去
In the future, it will become a lot of output
以后就变成很多很多的产量
A chicken with more teeth than a turkey
比火鸡比牙还多的鸡
However, there are quite a lot of Beijing dental
不过北京牙也是相当不少
So
那么
Peking duck was originally Nanjing duck
北京鸭原来是南京鸭
Later, when the five generations of fruit were opened
后来开了这个五代水果的时候
There is this river between Beijing and Nanjing
北京跟南京之间有这个用河
often up and down
常常有上上下下
At that time, Nanjing Duck gradually became Peking Duck
那个时候就南京鸭就慢慢地变成北京鸭
then look again
那么再看
What about the cross mark cross mark cross mark I just mentioned?
刚才我讲的这个叉号叉号叉号的东西呢
is this majestic
是这堂堂
Don is the tobacco we can say is given to us every week
堂是我们可以说是每周给我们的烟草
asian give them hall
亚洲给他们堂
It feels like this hall
感觉是这堂
The language of this church is English and it is called Sugar
这个堂的语言是英语是叫做Sugar
Sugar
Sugar
Arabia is that this is Sugar from Arabia
阿拉伯在于这是从阿拉伯来的Sugar
This is Boss Sugar
这是波士鱼的Sugar
Sugar from Indo to Sanskritito
那发于Indo于Sanskritito的Sugar
So now it's Sugar
那么现在就是Sugar
Italy in Sugar
意大利于Sugar
Budayain
布达亚因
In ancient times
古代发于
Ancient West
古代西
The other one is also Saccharis
其他一也是Saccharis
So mostly through this kind of words
所以多半是經過這種話來講
In this Tang character, it is said that the rice character adds soup
在這個唐字據說是米字加湯
is a fresh word
就是新鮮字
what about this
那麼這個呢
In fact, Tang has a long history
其實唐的歷史是很久很久
Indian record
印度先有記載
it is south of india with this pole
它是印度的南部有這個桿子
then as far back as 8 centuries before the park
那麼最早可以追溯到公園前8個世紀
Well, there are also records in China
那麼中國也有記載
Just said it was from India
剛才說是來自印度
so don't get close
那麼唐的接近
was found before the Gupda dynasty
是發現在Gupda王朝之前
It was the park 50 years ago
就是公園50幾前
Don's proximity is very important
這個唐的接近呢是非常重要
Before World War II After World War II
以前二戰二世戰以後
Taiwan's so-called governance of the Tang Dynasty
台灣的所謂治唐業
nearly destroyed
差不多被破壞了
then reply
然後再回覆
The biggest difficulty is getting this sugar in and out
最大的困难就是把这个糖接进出来
If the sugar does not come in and out
糖不接进出来的话
Zhichang is very, very difficult
智长就非常非常困难
just can't count
就是不能够核算
So whoever can access the sugar person's company first wins
所以谁能先接进糖的人的公司就赢
So there are many economic
那么说有很多经济
This is not the original
这个不是这个正传的
Okay so now when it comes to this
好 那么现在当讲到这个
During the Halsian Empire of North India
北印度的哈尔西亚帝国的时候
there used to be this pie
曾经有这个派
It's time to receive Changchao
是接到长朝的时候
can learn this simple method
都就可以学到这种干脆的方法
i also see
我也看到
a certain minister of a certain dynasty
某一个朝代的某一个大臣
to murder the emperor
要谋害这个皇帝
He gave him this candy every day
他就天天给他吃这糖
He will probably eat later
以后他就大概吃饭了
Of course it will become
当然要变成了
Is this minister small?
这个大臣是不是小
What I read about diabetes
我讀到的糖尿病的庙截
Or just stumbled across this thing I don't know
还是偶然发现这个东西我是不曉得
Anyway, there have been people who used sugar for reading a long time ago.
反正已经是有很早以前就有人会用糖来当作读书
So
那么
Bactonia, this is the so-called Great Alexander
巴克多尼亚这是所谓Great Alexander
When the third land once made an expedition to India
在第三大地 曾经远征到印度去的时候
Just take these and this file is called Honey bearing weas
就带这些这档叫做Honey bearing weas
It's not this file, it's sugar cane to bring back
就是不是这档 这是甘蔗带回去
Breed in Mattonia
在马特多尼亚种
Well Columbus is from Kennedy Island
那么哥伦布是从Kennedy Island
Got sugarcane weave not brought into the US
得到甘蔗织 没有带进美国
It sounds like Columbus is here
这个讲起来是哥伦布在这里
something to do with the queen here
跟这里的女王有点关系
this relationship
这个关系
I won't talk much
我不多講
so it goes through here to get dry
所以它經過這裡拿到乾澈
In order to be able to grow dry in the United States
才能夠在美國種乾澈
so we'll get to this
那麼我們就講到這個
FDN in the United States recommends daily
美國的FDN推薦每天
Get out this 2000 to 2500 calories
出去這個2000到2500卡的熱量
in the United States actually
在美國實際上
calories out per day
每天出去的熱量
much more than this
大大超過這個
For example, Cinnabon
比如說Cinabon
Everyone's little Cinabon in the lot
大家小的Cinabon在很多
American airports sell this
美國的機場賣的這個
As soon as a Cinabon comes out, this is equal to
一出一個Cinabon就是這個等於
123% of this stuff
123%的這個東西
a big bottle of cola
一個大瓶的可樂
it's about the same
是跟它差不多
Then there are so many Sherups in Pancake
那麼Pancake的Sherup也這麼多
ice cream 1 coffee has so much
冰淇淋1咖啡有這麼多
so what
所以呢
These things are very, very common to Americans
这些东西在美国人来看是非常非常寻常
So FDS is now recommended
所以FDS现在是推荐
can only eat so much
只能吃这么多
So the sugar community is too big
那么糖类社区太大
Everyone Knows To Be Fat
大家都晓得会胖
diabetes patient
糖类病患来
Also cures cancer, stops teeth and hurts liver
也治癌 住牙 伤肝
These are all very serious consequences
这些都是会造成非常严重的后果
Recently, Americans have become more self-conscious
最近在美国人比较有自觉
There was a doctor called Rovartalustic
有一个医生叫做Rovartalustic
It is the authority of the neurology of internal administration in the United States
是美国神经内服密科的权威
he once published a
他曾经发表过一个
Sugar The Beta Truth
Sugar The Beta Truth
Very Familiar Facts About Sugar
关于糖的非常熟络的事实
That's what he said
就是说他讲的一句
sugar is toxin
就是糖是毒素
really makes sense
真正是有道理的
So you see now America
所以你看現在美國
Every time I come back to the U.S. from a foreign country
我每次從外國回到美國去
The first thing I can see is the return of the Americans
第一件我先看得出來就是美國人的迴旮
it's very scary
這是非常可怕的
So it makes sense for him, the doctor, to say that Down's family read books.
所以他這位醫生講唐氏讀書是有道理
So try your best to use this as your goal
所以盡量大家就盡量用這個來做目標
This is actually a difference between men and women
這個是其實有男女之差
But anyway this
不過反正這個
If you think about it, one Monday exceeds the calories of the whole day
你想想看一個星期一就超過整天的熱量
so very very powerful
所以非常非常厲害
So look back at the short history
那麼再回看歷史短短的歷史
Then it is the same as below
那麼正和下是一樣
It is said that Zhenghe has also been to America, probably not
據說正和也曾經來過美洲大概不是
But if he comes
不過假如他來了以後
However, in America, Columbus was not so glorious
但是,在美國,哥倫布就沒有那麼大的光榮
However, Columbus came to the United States on the 41st, 4th, 9th, 2nd
不過,哥倫布是來到美國第四十一、四、九、二
Finally, one or two years
最後是一、二年
Exactly, I came to Taiwan a little later
正正,我來台灣是比較晚一點
Japan came to Taiwan later
日本來台灣更晚
Therefore, after the actual arrival in the United States,
所以,正合交的真正到美國來以後
The so-called topic I'm going to talk about today will be quite different.
所謂我今天講的題目就會大不一樣了
then, at the end
那麼,最後呢
That's about the end of what I'm talking about
我大概講的東西到此完了
However, in the end, I would like to thank you all
不過,最後還是要謝謝各位
There are a few people who can help
有幫忙的幾位
some people are here
有些人是在這裡
So, what about reference hazards
那麼,關於參考危險呢
in english, yes
英語方面呢,是
why we eat why we eat
為什麼我們吃,為什麼我們吃
starter chocolate
起子巧克力
food america to the world
食物美国给世界
Also food in history
另外食物在历史
This is Lie Yi Tae Xia
这是列宜 塔诶厦
It can be said that Qiao Wen has the most Qiao Wen's book is this
可以说是乔文有最有乔文的书是这位
Written by Zugman
祖哥曼写的
This 1998 is the time when it was published
这个1998是在版的时候的时间
the original was earlier
原版是早一点
Potato
Potato
How the humble spot
How the humble spot
spot is the thing that goes fast
spot就是快一快的那个东西
Rescue the western world
Rescue the western world
relatively new is
比较新的就是
Andrew Smith's Potato a global history
Andrew Smith写的Potato a global history
I read all these books
这些书我都看了
see all
全看
Then I just talked about this
然后刚才讲到这个
Written by Mr. Pan Fujun
潘富君先生写的
Smokey 朱继
Fumosa 朱继
This Taiwanese food culture system
这个台湾环食文化制
These two wrote
这位两位写的
Yaolan, a Taiwanese farmhouse, also has
台湾农家耀兰也有
There are two very impressive books in Japanese
日语里头有两本非常可观的
This is written by Ben Jingjian
这是本景剑级写的
Satsuma billion horse is
Satsuma 亿马就是
Another layer of the world of "Jackie Mo" written in Zhang characters
另外一層張字寫的《夾外衣莫》的世界
It is the world of Potato
就是Potato的世界
Both sides are wonderfully written and very evil
這兩邊都寫得非常精彩 非常惡要
Especially about the history of the development of feudal arts and foreign languages ​​in Japan
尤其關於在日本的藩術跟洋語的發展的歷史
is very very clear
是非常非常清楚
Finally thank you all
最後謝謝各位
Thank you Li Yuan Restaurant is a wonderful staff
謝謝李遠餐院是精彩人員講
I don't know if there is any problem doing it now
現在不知道在做有沒有問題
please
請
borrow a microphone
藉個麥克風
My question is to say
我要問的問題就是說
Basically I'm thinking of a question which is to say
基本上我在想一個問題就是說
Spaniards once came to Taiwan
西班牙人曾經來過台灣
Spaniards dated around 1626
西班牙人的時間大概是1626年
Then the Dutch also came to Taiwan
那麼荷蘭人也來過台灣
Then I was thinking that the Dutch came around this time in 1624
那我在想說荷蘭人是1624年大概這個時候來的
In other words, the migration of animals and plants in Taiwan came from these two lines
換句話說台灣的這個動植物的遷移是由這兩條線進來的
Because they went to the Philippines and Manila
因為他們有去菲律賓有去馬尼拉
So it is said that the New World was brought from there.
所以就說新大陸這個東西是從那邊帶過來的
It is possible that from the perspective of so we see a lot of conversations
有可能從所以我們來看很多是交話
There are many more like this, this, Batavia or Holland
還有很多是這個這個這個巴達維亞或者是荷蘭
Or India then one of the things I want to ask I want to understand is say in New Zealand
或者是印度那麼我想問的一個我想理解的一件事情就是說在西蘭
This place in New Zealand is now Sri Lanka
西蘭這個地方就是現在的斯利蘭卡
It was also occupied by the Netherlands in about 1652.
曾經也被荷蘭佔領過大概在1652年的時候呢
They did a research on Potenacr one by one
他們做了一個一個一個Potenacr的一個research
They found out that the Dutch
他們發現說呢荷蘭人
Because Zealand has a history of being occupied by the Netherlands and grapes
因為 西蘭有被荷蘭跟葡萄佔據的歷史
they found out
他們發現說呢
after the dutch left
荷蘭人離開之後
They did a species survey
他們去做了一個物種的調查
It turned out that fifty percent
竟然發現有百分之五十
It's exotic
是exotic 是外來種
In other words plants have an invisible velocity
換句話說植物有一種看不見的速度
invade zealand
入侵到西蘭去
So my question is that
那我的問題就是說
If Taiwan is counted from the year 1624
台灣從1624年那個年來算的話
The Dutch The Dutch have been in Taiwan for 42 years
荷蘭人 荷蘭人在台灣42年
After leaving, there must be an invisible speed
離開之後 想必也有一種看不見的速度
bring all his stuff in
把他所有的東西帶進來
what about that thing
那那個東西呢
That is, the academician may have talked about a lot
就是院士講的可能有很多
In terms of flipping or paste that thing
用翻或用糊那個東西來講
then just ask
那請問一下就是說
then Taiwan
那麼台灣
Now building has a problem saying
現在建設有一個問題說
That is to say Taiwan
這樣就是說台灣
Crash everywhere
崩潰到處
something is eating
有什麼東西在吃
when talking so much
就講這麼多的時候
what is there in taiwan
台灣到底有什麼東西
this is my first question
這是我第一個問題
The second question is to say
第二個問題就是說
The academician just said that there is a kind of vanilla
剛剛院士講的有一種 vanilla
Valina actually it's a Dutch
Valina actually 它是一個荷蘭
Vanilla its flavor it is an orchid called Vanilla Orchid
Vanilla 它的flavor 它是一個有一種蘭花叫Vanilla Orchid
Vanilla's Lan OK
Vanilla的蘭 OK
Extract its flavor from that orchid
從那個蘭裡面萃取出它的flavor
That is the fruit of a bean in the orchid
那那個是蘭花裡面的一個豆的果實
But what you just drew is a disease of a Vanilla
可是你剛剛畫出來是一個Vanilla的一個病
this bean
這個豆子
But the problem is that orchids will not cure such a serious disease
可是問題是蘭花不會解除那麼大的病
So I'm thinking that this disease is related to the small seeds in the orchid's fruit
所以我在想說這個病跟蘭花裡面的它的果實是小的種子
So I'm thinking about this Vanilla disease
所以我在想說這個Vanilla這個病
What is the difference between the so-called vanilla and the thing in the orchid? Two questions
跟這個所謂的Vanilla跟蘭花裡面的那個東西有什麼不同兩個問題
Thank you everyone
感謝大家
I hope you're not a pig
我希望你不是豬家
Vanilla is indeed a orchid pig
Vanilla的確是一個蘭科的豬
But I just showed you that this tomato also has vines and trees.
不過我剛才也給你看看這個番茄也有藤也有樹
so it doesn't have to be your orchid pig just watch this
所以不一定就是你的蘭科的豬就是看這個
Usually used for home decoration
平常在家內裝飾用的那種
So Manila is really blue, tree art blue
所以馬尼拉是真正是藍顆、樹藝藍顆
And it has to change to be able to
而且是要變才能夠
Only when Manila changes can there be things
馬尼拉變才能夠有東西
So what I just said
所以我剛才講的
Human beings must be burnt to be able to achieve transformation from birth to death
要人工受焚才能夠做到生到變
what about me
我的話呢
Until now, only when you go to land can you eat in Manila
到現在還是只要到進到陸去才有馬尼拉吃
About Not Just Plants
關於不僅是植物
all other disseminated
其他所有傳播的
It doesn't have to be a simple path
不一定是用很單純的一條路走
so there are many paths to take
所以有很多路徑可以走
what about this
這個呢
Wisme Qing'an
比如說維斯姆慶安
We are not so simple
我們也是不是那麼簡單
It's not that you eat a macroclump
不是你吃一顆大團菌
or what bacteria
或是什麼菌
will drop immediately
就立刻會弄掉
This very depends on the period of your contact
這個非常就是看你的這個接觸的期間
The purpose of contacting this party
跟接觸的這個當事人的用途
For example, the Dutch came to Taiwan
比如說荷蘭人到台灣來
Not very generous with the food they brought to Taiwan
並沒有很慷慨的把他們帶來的食物給台灣
Taiwanese people go to steal his to get Dutch beans
台灣人去偷他的才來有荷蘭豆
Dutch beans are not a free supply brought to Taiwan by the Dutch
荷蘭豆並不是荷蘭人帶給台灣的免費供給的
but stolen
但是偷來的
So this is not a line
所以這個就是不是一條線
So there may be many ways to talk about the sweet potato
所以剛才講的這個番薯也是可能有很多途徑來講
so can't say
所以不能夠講
I think Wang Fufu is probably smarter than me
我想王復復大概比我高明
history does not appear
歷史並不是出現的
I don't know if I answered your question or not
不曉得我有回答你的問題沒有
I want to share something and raise a question
我想分享一下一個東西,然後也提出一個疑問
That Gava 516, I once heard the director of the Mandarin Association talk about it
那個Gava 516,我曾經聽那個國語會主任委員他講說
Nabala is the language of their Paiwan people
那巴拉是他們那個排灣族的語
Paiwan language is called Nabbat, it is N-A, then a V-A-T
排灣族語叫Nabbat,它是N-A,然後是個V-A-T
It seems that the Paiwan language is developed independently, and there are also such sayings
好像是排灣族語是獨開的,也有這種說法
Nabbat is used in the south, and Nabbat has many sounds
Nabbat就在南部就被用Nabbat,Nabbat就有很多音出來
I once went to Yunnan, China to see a kind of Nabbat
我曾經到中國的雲南去看過一種也是Nabbat
Our general Balat size is probably like this or like this, right?
我們一般的Balat大小大概都這樣子或者這樣子對不對
It used to be like this, but after improvement, it will look like this
以前是這樣子,改良了就大這樣子
The kid I saw in Yunnan had such a big head
我在雲南看到的那個小孩子的頭那麼大
big
大
right
對
that tree too
那個樹也是
also that
也是那個
rice water stove tree
飯水爐的樹
same tree same leaves
一樣的樹 一樣的樹葉
I myself am
我自己本身是
also learn this
也是學這個的
so i think
所以我是覺得說
strangeness
奇怪
why so big
怎麼那麼大
should be delicious
應該很好吃
It turned out to be nasty
結果是很難吃
then i go
那麼我去
go with him
去跟他
sometimes you that
有時候你們那個
Why is this white spicy food so unpalatable?
這個白辣怎麼那麼難吃
He said
他說
what white spicy
什麼白辣
I said that not only what is this called
我說那不但這個叫什麼
Xiangyu
叫象域
nice name
名字很好聽
elephant area
象域
I just thought about it
就是想好的象那邊
domain domain dead domain
域 域死的域
Then I said how to eat this
那我說這個怎麼吃
He said
他說
eat with honey
沾著蜂蜜吃
how to eat
怎麼吃
oh
哦
that's all
就這樣
but i think
但是我覺得說
if say
假如說
in the country of origin
在原產地
If say in South America
假如說在南美的時候
Origin unknown
原產地不曉得多大
because
因為
His little boy has such a big head
他那個小孩子頭那麼大
It's delicious. It's really big.
就很吃 真的很大
I bought two and both were terrible
我買兩個都是很難吃
then i don't know what to say
那我就不知道說這個
is it from there
是不是從那邊
to Yunnan
傳到雲南
the one in the mountains
那個在山區
To be at the place where Teng Zichong
要在騰子衝的地方
right
對
but so big
但是那麼大
I doubt it
我就懷疑說
strange that
奇怪 那個
he can't possibly go there
他不可能說到那邊去
As a result, he didn't improve this breed.
這個品種結果他沒有改良啊
He is very evil
他很是改惡啊
Hard to say
很難說
what's the matter
這個是到底什麼回事
my next topic
我下一個話題
good very happy
好 非常高興
Let's listen to the principal
我們這個聽主理說
there are real scholars
有真正的學者
not like me fake
不像我這種冒牌的
hehe
呵呵
Hello Mr. Liu
劉老師您好
I am also researching
那個我本身也是研究
food history
食物的歷史
So I
所以我
Because I think it's hard to be a food scientist
因為我覺得食物學家很難
become a historian
成為歷史學家
It's hard to be a biologist
又很難成為生物學家
but i feel teacher
但是我覺得老師
can put both
可以把兩者
ken bai together
肯拜在一起
I think I have gained a lot
我覺得收穫很多
Then I think what the teacher said today
那我覺得今天老師講的
mainly to say
主要是說
this
這個
columbus food
各倫布的食物
some in Taiwan
在台灣的一些
More Biological Effects
比較偏向生物性的影響
nutritional impact
營養性的影響
This way I know there is a
這樣我知道有一個
John Hopkins teacher called
John Hopkins的老師叫
Cedrin Mines
Cedrin Mines
he studies sugar
他研究糖
Sugar, sugar can
Sugar, sugar can
with this sweetness
跟這個sweetness
in the caribbean
在Caribbean
in Western Africa
在Western African
with that british
跟那個英國
He combines this Triangle
他結合這個Triangle
U.K.
英國
then raised the sugar
然後提出了糖
A special place in modern history
近代歷史上比較特殊的地位
Then I think the teacher means
那我覺得老師就是說
of these countries
這些各國的
It is the food brought to Asia by the ministries of various countries
就是各國的部帶到亞洲的食物
Is it possible for us to say
我們有沒有可能說
if further discussion
如果進一步來討論
Is it possible to discuss culturally
有沒有可能在文化上討論出
special
比較特殊的
That is to say, there are
就是說比較有
Of course it doesn't have to be like Hitler
當然不一定要像希特利密子
like sugar
像糖那麼有
concrete things
具體性的東西
caused the final
造成了最後
Novelties of the Industrial Revolution
工業革命的新奇
But the teacher's research
但是就老師的研究
In terms of culture, does the teacher feel that
就文化上老師有沒有覺得說
these foods
這些食物
Is there anything about something in Taiwan
對台灣的東西有沒有什麼
Exotic food in these five hundred years
外來的食物在這五百年以來
is there anything special
有沒有什麼比較特殊
Influence on culture
在文化上的影響
Thanks
謝謝
The sweetest question is also quite interesting
這個最糖的問題也是蠻有趣的
Well what I just said is very simple
那麼我剛才講是很簡單
also a lot of this
也很多這個
Of course the path is from the world
當然路徑就是從世界
the whole world
整個世界來講
next to become a problem
旁成為問題
is imperialism
就是帝國主義
related to imperialism
跟帝國主義有關係
Governing the sugar industry is imperialism
治糖業是帝國主義
because of the sugar industry
因為治糖業
Because it requires a lot of low-cost labor
因為要需要很大的低價的勞動力
This can only be done with nationalism
這個只能用地國主義才能夠做得到
For example, India still uses very
比如說印度現在還是用非常
Tip-Level's coming to fight against Taiwan used to be
Tip-Level的來抗台灣以前也是
so so
那麼所以
this
這個
Of course, Wang Huyu often knows here
當然王沪宇很常常在這裡曉得
Dutch dry residue is mainly found in
荷蘭種乾渣主要是在
Pepper tiles are also planted
椒瓦也開始種
Other crabs have also started to grow
其他芭蟹也開始種
This is what some people say is for resistance
這個就是有人說是為了抵抗
Resist selling too much coffee and tea
抗拒咖啡跟茶賣得太多
so they use
所以他們就用
Use this to make up for it
用這堂來補償
did not lose
沒有輸
Because why the Netherlands also has this plant sugar
因為荷蘭為什麼對這個植糖也有
I will try my best to do it
会那么尽大的进去做
it dutch has had little success with coffee
它荷兰对咖啡也没有什么成功
Didn't have much success with tea either
对茶也没有什么成功
So I had no choice but to develop towards this roasted sugar
所以只好向这个炙糖来发展
So Zhitang in Taiwan is actually
所以炙糖在台湾的炙糖其实也是
Mostly based on the Dutch sugar industry
多半是根据荷兰的炙糖业来发展的
there are still problems
还有问题
In fact, we have always wanted to say
其实我们一直太想说
Don't forget Yabuy when the Dutch were in gay Taiwan
别忘了雅买家在荷兰人在同志台湾的时候
In fact, it also manages a place called Yagamaga
其实也管了一个地方叫雅加马加那个地方
But we often go that way, I think
可是我们常常那个路径我觉得
Too much reliance on the route of the so-called East India Company
太依赖所谓东印度公司这个路线
That is to say, we are too dependent on
也就是说我们太依赖
We rely too much on this so-called discourse
我們太依賴這個所謂的這個論述
Actually, I think it's a little bit wrong
其實我想想也是有點有點不太
I don't understand that
搞不太懂就是說
Why things must come from India
為什麼東西一定從印度
dug from the claws
從爪挖來
Because he manages two colonies at the same time
因為他同時管兩個殖民地啊
he can also from
他也可以從
amaica
亞買加
Because we don't have the Amaica way of thinking
因為我們比較沒有亞買加的思考方式
don't forget the one in amaica
別忘了亞買加的那個
the so-called that
那個所謂的那個
Hugo is famous
修葛是很有名的
what else is he famous for
還有他什麼很有名
His tobacco is also famous
他的菸草也是很有名的
That means he
那也就是說他
East India Company he came back from Amaica
東印度公司他從亞買加繞回來
When he went around in a circle, he took this so-called
繞到一圈的時候他順便再把這個所謂的
This, this, I speak Spanish
這個這個我講西班牙齁
He also brought Spanish goods to Taiwan
他同時也把西班牙的東西載到台灣來
So I think this if explained in this way
所以我想這個如果用這個方式去解釋的話
Would you be more inclined to say that?
是不是會比較偏向於說那個
It seems that 7-11 wants to distribute goods, you know
好像說7-11他要鋪貨你知道嗎
He is from Southern PU
他從南部PU
Then there is him in the north and HP
那麼北部有他又HP了
Then I think with such a principle
那我覺得用這樣的一個原理
to explain the path of propagation
來解釋傳播的路徑
will it replace say
會不會取代的說
If the Henan East India Company from Java or from India
如果河南東印度公司從爪哇或者從印度
I think if the East India system at that time is included
我覺得如果把那個時候東印度的系統納進去
Will the history of this practice make another
這個實務的歷史會不會做出另外一個
One by one one by one New interpretation
一個一個一個一個一個一個New interpretation
Of course, I'm talking about the more out-of-the-box one.
當然我講的是比較出放的一個
statement
說法
Then many scholars here can correct me
那麼在座的很多學者都可以糾正我
But what?
不過呢
You also know the 7-11
你也曉得這個7-11呢
from where
從哪裡來
7-11 in Taiwan is from Japan
台灣的7-11是日本來
Where did Japan's 7-11 come from?
日本的7-11從哪裡來
come from america
美國來
So how do you explain this?
那麼這個怎麼解釋呢
is also very difficult to explain
就是也是非常難解釋
What about the way something spreads?
一個東西傳播的途徑呢
As I said just now, it's not that simple
我剛才也講過並不是那麼簡單的
So, for example, where does the population of Japan come from?
那麼譬如說日本的人口從哪裡來
not from a certain country
並不是從某一個國家傳來的
Taiwanese
台灣的人
So of course what I'm talking about today is just a few examples
所以当然我今天讲的是只与几个例子而已
i'm dead i'm not an expert
我已经生命我不是专家
i just love food
我只是爱好食物的
So I can't argue with you what is the fact of the example
所以我也不能跟大家争到底是什么是例子的事实
I used to give you the ability to stimulate your imagination
我曾经给大家能够刺激你的想象
I will be very satisfied if I stimulate your interest
刺激你的兴趣的话我就会非常满足
Where
在哪里
you just said wood
你刚才说到木属
Wood
木属
Subterranean Continents of the World
世界地下大陆有木属
he said
他有说到
So what are the first and second largest crops?
那請問第一大跟第二大作物是什麼
This is also the definition
這個也是定義
then wheat rice
那麼小麥米
Does corn count as the third
玉米算不算第三
this is trainable
這個是可以訓練
So the most important thing is wheat and rice
所以最主要是小麥跟米
then uncle and corn
那麼叔叔跟玉米
it's hard to say
就很難講
sometimes you crop
有時候你作物
if you grow corn
假如你種玉米
make it alcohol
把它拿來做酒精
if you come to feed the car
來餵汽車的話
Is it counted as food?
是不是算做食物呢
even if it's fake
就算很假
two questions
兩個問題
the first is
第一個就是
How did you research this food
您怎麼會去研究這個食物
I didn't say it before
我以前不是講過
i gave out seven food
我出了七個食物
A biochemist studies Chinese things
生化家是研究國的東西的
It has a lot to do with this master
跟這個師父非常有關係
And I am directly motivated
而且我直接動機
I'm going to South America
我到南美去
When going to South America at the same time
同時到南美去的時候
See in person knuckle corn and more
親眼看到關節玉米等等
that's a direct deed
那是直接的事跡
on the other hand
另外一方面
I'm not a research practitioner
我也不是研究實務的
Experts who also study practice here
在這裡也研究實務的專家
as far as the 16th century
就16世紀
Many places in China refer to
中國很多地方的地方指
are starting to appear
都開始出現了
mentioned these things
已經提到了這些事
And they are all treated as new crops
而且都是當作新的作物
inside the reporter
在記者裡面
So it's always a matter of peace
所以一直和平地緣事
just wrote an article
才會寫過一篇文章
called "16th Century"
叫《16世紀》
"15 Classics"
《15經典》
including years in the mainland
在大陸包括幾年
Multiple ranks
多行列
Later there were some recordings
後來也有一些錄訊
that is
就是說
Just now because it seems that the one
剛才因為好像那一位
keep mentioning
一直在提到
just mentioned how to pass it on
就是提到這怎麼傳
is it possible
有沒有可能
One of them came from China
其中一個是從中國傳過來
This is Taiwan
就是台灣的這個
since the 16th century
因為從16世紀
Still in use in the 17th century
17世紀還一直在用
to the 18th century
到18世紀
When it comes to Qianlong
到錢龍的時候
also invited someone
還請了一個人
To promote the cultivation of sweet potatoes all over the country
要全國各地推廣種那個番薯
Because I also grow in many places
因為很多地方我也種
The character experience is about
那人物體驗是講的
Sweet Potato Saves Many People
番薯救很多人
including saving some
包括可以救過一些
Because sweet potatoes are so easy
因為番薯非常容易
And because China's more
而且因為中國的更地
more restrictive
更地是限制的
Population has been inflating
人口一直通脹
When many things cannot be planted
那很多東西沒辦法種的時候
Can't grow rice
水稻沒辦法種
are planted in the sand
都種在沙地
or hills of hills
或是山丘的小山丘
Those are the fish that rely on these peanuts
那些就是靠這些花生魚
sweet potato and so on
番薯等等這些
When there was no land for growing rice
原來沒種水稻的地的時候
can feed many people
可以養活很多人
and it's harvested very wide
而且它的收植非常寬
So this promotion is
所以這個推廣是有
not temporary
不是一時的
Doesn't seem like a source either
好像也不是一個來源
been promoting
一直在推廣
sweet potato is a very good
番薯就是一個非常好
until the time of channon
一直到錢農的時候
there is also a registration station
還有一個登記站
sent someone everywhere to promote
派了一個人到處在推廣
promotion sometimes he still has one level left
推廣有時候他還剩他一關
So this thing originated
所以這個東西起源
can be quite early
可以相當早
And there can be many sources
而且來源也可以非常多
and in fact it's not
而且事實上也不是
stop all at once
一次就全部停廣
but in fact has been
但事實上一直
You see, from the 16th century to the 18th century
你看從16世紀其實要18世紀
And record things like overthrowing the book
還有記載一下推翻書之類的事情
So it's not like Hua Shengmin's first record
所以就是說這不是像是華盛民第一次最早記載的
Alive Asan, a Portuguese
活者阿三一個葡萄牙人
He is like a Chongqing in the civil war
他好像民武中的一個重慶
He seems to be the first time that Huasheng Democracy enters China
他好像是第一次萬一華盛民進中國的這個
But it was still there until later
可是一直到後來還是一直有在裡面
And the source is not one
而且來源也不是一個
so what i mean is
那麼我的意思就是說
Seems like everything should be done
好像看起來就是所有事情應該這些東西都能做到
Or Taiwan or East Asia has some of the most exhausting resources from Central America
或台灣或是東亞有一些最累的中美洲來的資源
Possibly also from China
可能也有從中國來的
Not necessarily an autonomous introduction to Manila or something
不一定是自治介紹馬尼拉或是什麼東西
Yes I have a picture that is
對 我有一個圖是
This arrow goes to many places
這個箭頭是到很多地方
But this is also a question of quantity
不過這個也可以說量的問題
So you said the amount from China
所以你說從中國來的量
What is the amount following through Manila
跟從經過馬尼拉來的量是哪一個
if say or even talk
假如說甚至要講就
This is where it comes from
這個是從那裡來的話
you can give three four five
你可以舉個三個四個五個
to say this
要講這個的話
maybe three or four hours
可能大概要三四個小時
and i didn't say it
而且我不是我講的
i can't talk that much
我不能講那麼多
I just wanted to add to that
我剛剛願意補充一下剛剛那個
friend's opinion
朋友的意見
I think we're talking about a
我覺得我們在講的一種
origin of species
物種的起源論
means to believe in that species
就是說相信那個物種
Where does the special compared to the original come from?
比較original的special是從哪裡來的
Then we come from this thing
那我們從這個東西來
found that
發現說
how it spread
它怎麼傳播出去
The last one you mentioned just now has
剛剛您說的那個最後中國有
I think that's what I agree with
我覺得這個就我同意
That is to say, the path of this possibility is very different.
就是說這個可能千奇的路徑很不同
For example, the academician just talked about the spread of water birds
譬如說院士剛剛講的有水鳥的傳播
spread with ducks
有鴨子的傳播
As for returning to species, where is
至於說回歸到物種是在哪裡
would i think this is not a
會有我覺得這個是不是一個
We learn from the spiritual law of spiritual love
我們從靈愛的命靈法裡面
go find that answer
去找那個答案
Will it always form a situation of different opinions and different styles with Chinese culture?
是不是會一直跟中國的文化形成一種各說各化的局面
I think today is a comparison
我覺得今天是一個比較
I personally research this rather headache problem
我個人研究這個比較頭痛的問題
Just came across the Egyptian texts
就是碰到那種埃及文獻裡面
Or something like that in Turkish literature
或者是土耳其文獻裡面都有那樣的東西
But how do we face this theory of origin?
可是我們怎麼去面對這個起源說
This I ask the academician is a scientist
這個我請教院士是個科學家
That is, where did the species originate from?
就是說這個物種從哪裡起源
Can you tell me for sure how much you just said is decided
可不可以確定說你剛剛說多少決定了
Diversity determines the origin of that species
多樣化決定了那個物種的原鄉
If so
那如果這樣來講的話
Does the area also determine the number of species?
是不是面積也決定了物種的數量
so to speak
那這樣來講的話
Is it possible that it could happen elsewhere
有沒有可能在別的地方也會有可能發生
Thanks
謝謝
this is also possible
這個也可能
So often it turns out that
所以常常證明的是
where is the origin of human
人類的起源是哪裡
Currently considered African
目前是認為非洲
Russi is one, it's based on DNA
Russi是一個,這是根據DNA來看的
If you look at it in other ways in the future
假如將來用其他的方法來看的話
not necessarily that
不一定是那樣
But now the DNA evidence is very strong
不過現在目前DNA的證據是非常強
For example, recent reports say
比如說最近的報告說
Polaber
北極雄Polaber
where does it come from
它從哪裡來?
it's from aylan
它是從愛蘭的
Hui Xiong came
輝熊來的
And it was a female female bear
而且是一次母的母熊來的
This is based on DNA evidence
這是根據DNA的證據來講
is so
是這樣
what about this species
那麼這個物種呢
So what about species?
那麼這個講到物種呢這個
The question comes immediately, what is called seed
問題就立刻就來什麼叫做種
In the past, they were able to mate with each other, and vice versa.
以前就是能夠互相交配反之的就是種
But now this view has also become very complicated
不過現在這個看法也變得非常複雜
so it can't be simple
所以不能夠很簡單
Then you can judge where this came from. It’s so simple.
那你去斷論說是這個是從哪裡來這麼簡單說
What I just said is that Japan’s ethnicity comes from many sources.
我剛才講的就是說日本的民族哪裡來很多來源
He can talk about the Japanese nation from the outside if he talks about it from the past.
把他一切從過來講日本的民族是從外頭來就可以講
i ask a final question
我問一個最後的問題
I like food very much
我是很喜歡吃食物啦
Then I came here today and saw that many of the things written in it are what I like to eat
那我今天來這裡看到裡面寫的很多東西都是我喜歡吃的
But unfortunately after listening to your talk, I found out that these things are all alien species
但是不幸的聽你講以後才發現這些東西都是外來種
so maybe
所以可能
After listening to today, I will probably go back to find something that is native to Taiwan.
聽完今天以後我回去大概就是要去找找什麼東西是台灣本種的
Because if they all eat exotic species, it means that I am also a foreigner.
因為不過全部都是吃外來種的話是代表我也是外國人
This is the first point
這是第一點
second point
第二點啦
Just now the academician mentioned something that I think is very important to everyone
剛才院士有提到一個我是覺得很重要對所有的人
Because you are important in life
因為你生來講都很重要的
That is to say, I just mentioned that the white chocolate cannot be eaten.
就是說剛才提到說那個白巧克力不能吃嘛
Also not good
另外不好
but a lot of yours like to eat dark chocolate
但是很多你的都喜歡吃黑巧克力
But it also mentioned that sugar is poisonous
但是又提到說糖是有毒的
Does that chocolate have sugar in it?
那巧克力裡面都有糖嘛
So how many pills can they eat?
所以呢 到底他們能夠吃幾顆
is it ok
OK嗎
Because my wife likes chocolate very much
因為我太太很喜歡吃巧克力啦
So I have to limit the amount of it
所以我一定要限制它的量喔
so there will be no problem
才不會出問題
no white chocolate
不能送白巧克力
If it is black, let it eat as much as possible
假如是黑的讓它盡量吃
eat less white
白的就少吃一點
This is mine
這是我的 我串大家的意見
But of course you tell people not to smoke
不過當然你叫人家不抽菸
People still smoke
人家還是會抽菸的
So you tell people not to eat white chocolate
所以你叫人家不吃白巧克力
People still eat
人家還是會吃
Of course, you'll be more at ease after you get married.
當然你結婚了以後就比較放心啦
It seems that there is another hand raised
好像還有一位舉手
The humorous questions asked by the two groups
那兩組問的比較幽默的問題
I'm asking a less humorous question
我問一個比較不幽默的問題
That seems to be a lot of people recently
那個最近好像很多很多人
In particular, Dean Li is very worried that the population is expanding so fast
尤其李院長很擔心說人口膨脹的這麼快
Food will be a problem in the future
以後糧食是個問題
From Academician Li's point of view
以李院士的看法
what kind of food
那哪一種糧食呢
It is the most likely solution to our human feeding problem
是最有可能解決我們人類餵糧食的問題
this is a problem
這是一個問題
Another question is
另外一個問題是
It is also a relatively big problem
也是算比較大的問題
Biofuel is a problem
Biofuel is a problem
I've been discussing issues now
我現在一直是在討論問題
so-called ground personnel
所謂的地色人員
those foods
那這些食物
not necessarily food
不一定是食物
just these foods
就這些食物
Which one academician Li thinks is the most likely
哪一種李院士認為最有可能
Is there any hope that this will help people out
有沒有這種希望能夠幫人們解決
this person's problem
這個人員的問題
Nor does it depend on Nucleic energy
也不是靠和Nucleic energy
or other such
或其他這種
if let me solve it
假如讓我解決的話呢
I think reducing the population is the only way
我是認為減少人口是唯一的方法
this is hard to do
這個很難做得到
But you can count
不過你有算就可以算
There are limits to using the biological revolution to produce food
用生物的革命來做這個生產糧食有限制
Earth's sunlight is limited Earth's yang energy is limited
地陽光有限制 地陽氣有限制
So the earth's resources are limited
所以地球的資源是有限的
So we can't just use the so-called Green Revolution to solve it
所以不能夠光用所謂Green Revolution來解決
And the so-called Biofield these so-called substitutes
而且所謂Biofield這些所謂代替的
For example, like using this hall to make alcohol for cars
比如說像把西用這堂來做酒精來為汽車
Of course it's a sacrifice, and it's also a sacrifice of this land.
當然是犧牲 也是犧牲這個土地
Where you should grow food grow dryness
你應該種糧食的地方就種乾澀
you grow less food to eat
你就少種可以吃的東西
This can be solved in the short term
這個短期可以這麼解決
long-term problem
長期就問題非常大
so i think
所以我是認為
Will this reduce the population is the only way
會這個減少人口是唯一的方法
Maybe this society has offended many people
可能這個各社會得罪很多人
our last question
我們最後一個問題
Thanks
謝謝
A very wonderful speech by an academician today
一院士今天的非常精彩演講
really learned a lot
真的就是學到很多東西
So I'll take a more personal question
那麼我以一個就是比較私人的問題
To end today is a question and answer
來結束今天的就是問答
is your interest in food whether it is your personal interest
就是您對食物不管是您個人的興趣
Or academically, professionally
或者是在學術上的就是專業的研究
so professional
都這麼的專業
Then I think Academician, do you have a set?
那我想院士您是不是有一套
It is a personal philosophy of this diet
就是個人的這個飲食的哲學
Would you like to share with you
是否願意跟大家分享一下
The first one has already been mentioned
第一個已經講到了
with white chocolate
配白巧克力
The second is
第二就是
So it's better to eat less and not more
所以說最好是少吃一點不要多吃
This is the first one
這是第一個
not study
不是學習
This is how it can be calculated
這是算起來可以怎麼算
I just calculated the calorie requirement
我剛才算這個calorie requirement
I can show you
可以給大家看
Americans eat too much calorie
美國人吃太多calorie
So should reduce
所以要應該減少
Because there are too many problems
因為是毛病太多了
and you put diabetes
而且你放糖尿病
The so-called cost of medicine
醫藥所謂的費用上面
Considerable for the country as a whole
整個國家來看是相當可觀
not only impressive but also terrible
不但是可觀是可怕
So I think I don't care about these two points.
所以我想這兩點翻起我倒不管
almost
差不多
Doctor Li is very good today
李醫院士今天人家很精采
very humorous
很幽默很減藥
so thank you all for coming today
那麼謝謝大家今天來
Thanks
謝謝
thank you all
謝謝大家
redundant
redundant